<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning Ireland and the different interests thereof, in answer to the Exon and Barnstaple petitions shewing, that if a law were enacted to prevent the exportation of woollen-manufactures from Ireland to foreign parts, what the consequences thereof would be both to England and Ireland.</title>
            <author>Brewster, Francis, Sir, d. 1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232233</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900165</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900165</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2525:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning Ireland and the different interests thereof, in answer to the Exon and Barnstaple petitions shewing, that if a law were enacted to prevent the exportation of woollen-manufactures from Ireland to foreign parts, what the consequences thereof would be both to England and Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Brewster, Francis, Sir, d. 1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Nott at the Queen's-Arms the Pall-Mall, and are to be sold by E. Whitlock at Stationers-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697/8.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  Law and legislation --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170932:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning IRELAND AND THE Different INTERESTS thereof, In Anſwer to the <hi>Exon</hi> and <hi>Barnſtaple</hi> Petitions; SHEWING, That if a Law were Enacted to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Exportation of <hi>Woollen-Manufactures</hi> from <hi>IRELAND</hi> to Foreign Parts, what the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences thereof would be both to ENGLAND and IRELAND.</p>
            <q>Pro Aris &amp; Focis.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>NDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Nott</hi> at the <hi>Queen's-Arms</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Pall-Mall,</hi> and are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by <hi>E. Whitlock <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1697/8.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:170932:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170932:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>HAving ſeen in the Votes of the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> the Contents of two Petitions, one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by the Inhabitants of <hi>Exon,</hi> and the other by thoſe of <hi>Barnſtaple,</hi> &amp;c. which (in the Opinion of all ſuch as I have converſed with, who know the Affairs of <hi>Ireland</hi>) have a malign and fatal Aſpect upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt and the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church of that Nation; and being deſired by ſome well-wiſhers to both Countries, to publiſh my Thoughts upon this Subject, I think my ſelf bound by the Sacred Tyes of Religion as well as the Common Obligations of Nature, to gratify their Deſires in this Particular: and do hope to make appear in the following Tract, that the fore mentioned Petitions are not only the moſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, but the moſt unconſcionable Requeſts that could be made to that <hi>Auguſt Aſſembly;</hi> for if they mean (as it is univerſally believ'd they do) that the <hi>High Court of Parliament,</hi> to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify the Petitioners Requeſt, ſhould enact a Law to prevent the Exportation of Woollen Manufactures from <hi>Ireland</hi> to Foreign Parts, and conſequently to Ruin the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi> I know nothing more extravagant which they could have deſired, unleſs it were that a Law ſhould be enacted againſt the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> or the City of <hi>London;</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> having been upon all Occaſions, ſince they were a People, the trueſt and ſtancheſt Friends the Monarchs and People of <hi>England</hi> ever had.</p>
            <p>I had (I confeſs) ſome Thoughts relating to this Affair the laſt Seſſion of Parliament, but after the prorogation thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſuaded by ſome I converſed with, that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> would not proceed further upon that Matter, I forbore to make them publick; but ſeeing the fore-mentioned Petitions, I am forced to put them together after the beſt manner I can, in that ſmall compaſs of time, I have for doing it, ſo that it cannot well be expected the following Paper ſhould appear ſo correct and
<pb facs="tcp:170932:3"/>accurate as it might, if I had time either to conſider further of it, or conſult my Friends, but Truth, I hope, will not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, becauſe She appears in a mean and humble Habit; and I do affirm, that to the beſt of my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver nothing elſe in this Diſcourſe. There may perhaps ſome ſmall Miſtakes be occaſioned through haſte or inadvertency, but the main Scope of it is Fair and Honeſt, and I ſhall not in any one particular endeavour to impoſe upon thoſe to whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration it is ſubmitted.</p>
            <p>It may perhaps be objected that I might have written more politely, if I had done it with that brevity which is now uſual upon other Occaſions; but indeed the Subject is of ſo great Conſequence, that I think I have not altogether done right to it, having to avoid Prolixity, omitted ſeveral things I might have ſaid; and I would deſire thoſe who may think it tedious, or whoſe Occaſions may not ſuffer them to read the whole, to omit the firſt part which is Hiſtorical, and begin at Page 37 where that which is moſt material begins to be treated of, and which will not take up much time in the peruſal.</p>
            <p>The great Motive (I am told) which induced the Weſtern People to prefer Petitions againſt <hi>Ireland,</hi> is the Notion they have of our being grown Rich and full of Money and Trade ſince the late War, which was undoubtedly occaſioned, partly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, becauſe one particular People among us (of whom I ſhall ſpeak at large in the following Pages) have engroſſed the greater part of what Riches there are in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and make a greater figure than ever they did before; and partly by the unwary Diſcourſes of ſome of our own Country that travel into <hi>England;</hi> who cannot bear the very beginnings of Proſperity, and are ſo vain-glorious, that they think they cannot ſufficiently extol their own Riches and Magnificence, (when God knows that) poor <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in her higheſt Proſperity never was, nor is like to be guilty of ſo unpardonable a Sin, as being Rich to that degree, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation ſhould have cauſe to envy her, or be jealous of her.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170932:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning IRELAND, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE greateſt and the wiſeſt Nations under Heaven, being ſubject to human Frailties, are apt ſometimes to conceive wrong Notions of things; and I know no Opinion more ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and withal, more univerſally received by the People of <hi>England,</hi> than that which they entertain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that unhappy Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> which of all the Territories that they have by their powerful and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Arms ſubdued to the Obedience of this Crown, has been (as they imagine, and would perſwade others) the moſt dearly purchaſed; They generally believe, that <hi>Acel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dama</hi> to have coſt <hi>England</hi> greater Numbers of Men, and vaſter Quantities of Treaſure, computing the Expence of both, from the time that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had firſt footing there, till the Concluſion of the late War, than it really did the <hi>Greeks</hi> to Conquer the World by the Proweſs of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great; or the <hi>Romans</hi> to do the ſame under the Conduct of <hi>Julius Caeſar.</hi> For we are told by Hiſtorians, that the Armies commanded by thoſe Generals, were recruited by every freſh Victory they obtained, and the People that had one Day the misfortune to be ſubdued by them, muſt the next Day aſſiſt in the Deſtruction of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170932:4"/>
            <p>The Spoils of conquered Nations in hand, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Empire at length, were the great Encouragements thoſe Conquerors had to undergo their Toils and Labours. The Riches of the Foreign World were their principal Funds for the payment of their Forces; and tho' it would be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to imagine, that they had not frequently (and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially upon all urgent Occaſions) Succors from their own Countries; yet thoſe great things which in their different Ages in the World, are attributed to them, were principally atchieved at the Expence both of the Blood and Treaſures of their vaſſal and tributary Provinces, which daily increaſed as they went forward with their Conqueſts.</p>
            <p>But a great many of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation are fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that the courſe of their Victories in <hi>Ireland</hi> was not ſo ſwift and eaſy, but that the Methods by which it hath been brought under ſubjection have been very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and the Work much more difficult and tedious.</p>
            <p>For that being a poor and moneyleſs Country, there were no very great Encouragements for an Army to Conquer it, ſo that it was gained by piece-meal, and <hi>England</hi> was at the whole Expence of ſubduing it; for from the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> II. till the latter end of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Days, being 432. Years, it was not entirely conquered; in which time Seventeen Kings and Two Queens governed ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>England:</hi> for which Reaſons they conclude, that it muſt of neceſſity have coſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation vaſt Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Men, and great Sums of Money, to keep their Ground, which they gained there from time to time, and at length to bring that whole Kingdom under ſubjection to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And running away with this as an undoubted Maxim and Truth, they conclude, <hi>That it had been much better for</hi> England, <hi>that God had left</hi> Ireland <hi>out of the Book of the Creation, or placed it in ſome diſtant Corner of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Concluſion will fail of courſe, when I ſhew the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170932:4"/>miſtake of the foregoing Opinion, which will be the eaſieſt thing imaginable to do, if they will allow their own Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles and the Writings of their moſt Authentic <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, to be the Rule of our Belief concerning the manner and means of <hi>Ireland</hi>'s being Conquered by <hi>England.</hi> For which end I here intended to have inſerted a brief Abſtract of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtory, ſo far as it relates to <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> II. to the Concluſion of the late War; but I find this in a great meaſure done to my hand by one Mr. <hi>W. H.</hi> in his Book entitled, <hi>Remarks on the Affairs and Trade of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland; printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1691. to which I refer ſuch as think it worth their while to be ſatisfied more at large: And therefore I ſhall only deſire thoſe who think <hi>Ireland</hi> to have coſt <hi>England</hi> ſo dear, to conſult the Hiſtories which are written concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that Kingdom by their own Authors, and they will find that the firſt Number of Men ſent over by <hi>Strongbow</hi> Earl of <hi>Chepſtow</hi> and <hi>Pembroke,</hi> under the Command of <hi>Fitz-Stephens</hi> and <hi>Fitz-Gerrald,</hi> was but 400. which were fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſoon after by <hi>Legroſs</hi> with 130. and in three Months after by <hi>Strongbow</hi> himſelf with 1200. more, being in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1170. the whole three Numbers amounting but to 1730. which was the Complement of the Army, that by the Aſſiſtance of <hi>Mac Murragh</hi> King of <hi>Leinſter</hi> and his Friends, did not only recover that King's Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Leinſter,</hi> but very much enlarge them, and in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, made the Kings of <hi>England</hi> Lords of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all this was done at the private Expence of <hi>Strongbow,</hi> and his Friends; as the remaining Provinces of that Kingdom were moſt, if not all of them, ſubjected to the Crown of <hi>England</hi> at the Expence of particular Perſons, who notwithſtanding, were well rewarded for their Services, by the grants of thoſe vaſt Eſtates which were given them by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and which many of their Succeſſors enjoy to this Day.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170932:5"/>
            <p>'Tis true that King <hi>Henry</hi> III. in the Year 1172. landed there in Perſon, with a Party which ſome ſay, conſiſted of 4500. but others only of 500 Knights; but had no occaſion to make uſe of them, for upon his arrival, the Natives of the three Provinces of <hi>Leinſter, Munſter,</hi> and <hi>Connaught</hi> were ſo terrified, that five of their Kings became tributary to him; by which means he did not only cut off the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication which <hi>France</hi> held with <hi>Ireland</hi> theretofore, from whence they had conſiderable Succours whenever the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> waged War againſt them; but he had himſelf, in four Years after, a very conſiderable Subſidy out of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. His Succeſſors alſo had frequently great Aids of Men, Money, and Proviſions from thence, which were great Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in their ſeveral Wars againſt the <hi>French, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Welch;</hi> all which is owned by the moſt Authentic <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtorians that have written upon this Subject. And 'tis certain that they make it plainly appear that the People of <hi>England</hi> from their firſt entrance into <hi>Ireland</hi> for 400 Years, which reached to the middle of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, were conſiderable gainers by that Kingdom, and that there were greater Numbers of Men, and more Money, and Proviſions ſent from thence into <hi>England, France</hi> &amp;c. in the ſeveral Kings Reigns that govern'd during thoſe Years, who were generally involved either in Civil Wars in the Heart of <hi>England,</hi> or in Foreign Wars againſt the <hi>French, Scotch</hi> or <hi>Welch,</hi> than were ſent out of <hi>England</hi> all that time towards the Reduction or Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For tho' there were frequent Rebellions raiſed in <hi>Ireland</hi> before the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> yet they were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally quaſh'd by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Country and ſuch of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> as adhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to them, with very little Coſt to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> till that grand Rebellion which was raiſed by <hi>Tyrone</hi> and others, who were ſet on and encouraged by the Pope (who by his publick <hi>Bull</hi> excommunicated Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170932:5"/>and the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi>) and were aſſiſted with Men and Money by the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For till the Pope's Supremacy was invaded, and Religion reformed, moſt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> except the Grandees of them, that loſt their Eſtates, by Conqueſt at firſt, or by Rebellion after they had ſubmitted to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> with their particular Friends and Adherents, moſt of the reſt, I ſay, were well enough ſatisfied with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, under which they lived much more ſecurely and happily, than they did under their own Petty Kings, who were daily Killing and Robbing, and uſing all manner of Acts of Hoſtility towards each other.</p>
            <p>But the Pope being diſobliged, the Quarrel ceaſed to be (as formerly) between <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> on account of Civil Intereſt, and was taken up between Proteſtant and Papiſt, on account of Religion, for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſts joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> as did ſome <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants with the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> on the other hand, and the Papiſts of both kinds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Enemies to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> by the inſtigation of their Prieſts and Friars, as we muſt expect they will ever remain while thoſe Incendiaries are ſuffered to continue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them.</p>
            <p>And the Truth of the Matter is, that the antient <hi>Iriſh</hi> being a poor diſpirited, and cowardly People, that is, the generality of them, they would in all probability run with as much dread from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as the <hi>Spartan</hi> Slaves did from their Maſters, to their ſeveral Imployments, when they appeared with no Arms, but Whips in their Hands; were they not aſſiſted and managed by the degenerate <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who are the moſt deſperate and troubleſome Enemies the Proteſtants have in that Nation.</p>
            <p>For the Proof of which we need not look further back, than the late Rebellion, for the Chief among the very firſt, that began about <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> 1688. to drive away the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants Cattel in the Counties of <hi>Mayo</hi> and <hi>Galway</hi> in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170932:6"/>Province of <hi>Connaught,</hi> where the Rappareeing Trade began, were of antient degenerate <hi>Engliſh</hi> Families, ſuch as the <hi>Jordans, Stanfords, Joyces, Garvys,</hi> and ſeveral others, whoſe Predeceſſors were antiently tranſplanted thither from <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the Army which was raiſed there for the late King <hi>James,</hi> it could never have been brought to be any way conſiderable, had none joyned in it but the antient <hi>Iriſh.</hi> We know that <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> and <hi>Sarsfield</hi> who were the Two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Commanders among them, were both of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. And 'tis remarkable that moſt of thoſe Families that were the chief Inſtruments in the Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> are this Day, or at leaſt were in the late War, the moſt dangerous and perverſe Enemies the <hi>Engliſh</hi> met with in that Kingdom; and particularly the <hi>Burks</hi> or <hi>de Burgo's,</hi> the Chief of which Name was ſo eminently ſerviceable in the Conqueſt of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that the Eſtate which was granted him in conſideration of that Service, was thought ſufficient to recommend an Heireſs of that Family <hi>Elizabeth de Burgo,</hi> to <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> third Son to <hi>Edward</hi> III. King of <hi>England,</hi> the yearly Rent thereof, even in thoſe Days, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing computed at 30000 Marks.</p>
            <p>But in the late War, that Family has been ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſerviceable to <hi>England,</hi> that I knew my ſelf four Lords of the Name who were Colonels of Regiments; by which we may imagine what a Number of this Family was in all other Poſts in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army. The Principal of thoſe Lords, <hi>Clanrickard,</hi> a half-witted, hot headed Zealot, being (to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy his fooliſh Ambition of being thought great) made a kind of a Sham-Governour of the Town of <hi>Galway,</hi> would have in one Day (by the Advice of ſome of the malicious Inhabitants of that place) ſacrificed to his Rage and Folly, the Lives of Sir <hi>Thomas Southwel</hi> and all his Party, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Two and Three Hundred Proteſtant Gentlemen, which he certainly had done, had he not been prevented by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170932:6"/>others who had the Senſe to conſider that they might very probably be called in a little time, to a ſevere Account, for ſo horrid and barbarous a Murder.</p>
            <p>Another, by his Title <hi>Galmoy,</hi> was Colonel of Horſe, and ſpared no Proteſtant with whom he could find any manner of pretence to pick a Quarrel; he was the firſt (that I heard of) who drew blood in the late War, having hanged up <hi>Carleton</hi> and <hi>Dixy</hi> at a Sign Poſt in <hi>Beltur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot,</hi> without any manner of Tryal, either by Martial or Common Law; after which the Rabble cut off their Heads, and kicked them through the Street as Foot-balls. He alſo occaſioned ſeveral other Gentlemen in the Queens Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, after they had made Terms for their Lives, to be hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and quartered at <hi>Maraburrough,</hi> for which Reaſons he has thought fit to Tranſport himſelf to <hi>France,</hi> where he ſtill remains. The other two Lords of that Family, were one of them taken Priſoner, and the other kill'd at <hi>Aghrim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hugh Lacy</hi> was alſo one of thoſe that in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> II. at his own expence Conquered the Kingdom of <hi>Meath,</hi> which is a conſiderable part of <hi>Ireland:</hi> And his Succeſſors are moſt, if not all of them bigotted Papiſts, one of them I knew in the Year 1687. to be principal of the <hi>Dominican</hi> Fryars in the City of <hi>Limerick;</hi> his Father had been a Colonel in the Rebellion of 1641. and was one that bore a great Sway in that Country at that time; and tho' I do not know what Imployments the reſt of that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily had, yet I do not doubt, but they were, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power, active and vigorous in carring on the late War.</p>
            <p>And I may juſtly give the ſame Account of the <hi>Fitz-Stephens</hi> and a great many of the <hi>Fitz-Gerralds,</hi> whoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors Commanded the firſt Forces that <hi>Strongbow</hi> ſent into <hi>Ireland,</hi> tho' the chief of the latter be a Proteſtant and the firſt Earl of <hi>Ireland.</hi> There are alſo ſeveral of the ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Engliſh Families who continue Papiſts, and have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170932:7"/>been as deeply engaged in the War as their Neighbours.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe particular Families, there are, in one part of that Kingdom, a whole Generation of People called the <hi>Natives,</hi> or the <hi>Birth of Galway</hi> (as they ſtyle themſelves) who were reckoned before the late War to have been worth 30000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> in Lands in the Province of <hi>Connaught,</hi> beſide their Trade or Merchandize by which they purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their Eſtates: They conſiſt of 14 Families, which they call <hi>Tribes,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Lynch, French, Blake, Kirwan, Dean, Skerret, Bodkin, Morris, Athy,</hi> &amp;c. the generality of which are ſo far from owning themſelves to be <hi>Iriſh men,</hi> that they care not for intermarrying, nor to have any dealings with the ancient <hi>Iriſh,</hi> more than the purchaſing their Lands, or receiving their ready Money for Wines, and other Merchandize: They were at firſt a Colony of Fiſher-men, and when they began to Trade to Sea, and grew great and rich by that means, were frequently mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted, and Plundered by the old <hi>Iriſh,</hi> ſo that they were conſtrain'd to make their Application to King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. from whom they obtained a Charter, with great Privileges and Immunities, by which they were enabled yearly to chooſe their own Clergy-men, in oppoſition to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Tuam,</hi> and were, in ſhort, put thereby in a poſture of defending themſelves <hi>contrà gentem quandam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram &amp; barbaram Offlaherty,</hi> which are the words of their Charter. This Town in the Rebellion of 41. was one of the laſt in that Kingdom that ſurrendred to the Earl of <hi>Munrath,</hi> upon very advantageous Articles, as it did this laſt War to General <hi>Gynckhel.</hi> In the Year 1688. the Mayor of that Town, one <hi>Brown</hi> by name, had a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for a Regiment ſent him by <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> which was accordingly raiſed there and in the Neighbourhood. There were alſo a great many of the Natives of that Town, who were Field-Officers, Captains, and Subalterns in other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments in that Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170932:7"/>
            <p>Now there is no doubt to be made, but thoſe Papiſt; of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Extraction, in conjunction with the Old <hi>Iriſh,</hi> have been very injurious to the People of <hi>England,</hi> and have put them to a vaſt Expence both of Men and Money, as well in this late War, as in that of <hi>Tyrone</hi> in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and that horrid Rebellion of Forty One, in which (according to the beſt Accounts we have) above 200000 Proteſtants of all Sexes and Ages were barbarouſly murdered in cold Blood; but this will not be ſufficient to prove that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have been looſers by <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that it were better for them there were no ſuch Country in the World. For let us but conſider the State of that Nation in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. and the yearly Benefit which 'tis apparent to the World <hi>England</hi> made of it, and we ſhall find it demonſtrable, that 'tis a mere vulgar Error, either to think or ſay ſo.</p>
            <p>For it is plain Matter of Fact, that in the latter end of that King's Reign, and the two or three firſt Years of the late King <hi>James</hi>'s, that they received Forty Thouſand Pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> which was or might have been tranſmitted to them into <hi>England</hi> out of the Revenues of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained clear to them over and above the Charge of the whole Eſtabliſhment of that Kingdom, that is both of the Military and Civil Liſt, which amounted to 243663 <hi>l. Sterl.</hi> to this we may add above 10000 <hi>l.</hi> a Year paid out of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue in Penſions to ſeveral Perſons reſident in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Rents alſo of Lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> which belong to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proprietors, or at leaſt which were conſtantly ſpent in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> amounted to 100000 <hi>l.</hi> yearly, and 'tis affirmed by them that beſt underſtood the Trade of that Nation, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by their Shipping imployed in carrying Coals for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in Merchandizing otherwiſe for the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> to ſeveral Parts of the World, gained above 70000 <hi>l.</hi> clear, <hi>per annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170932:8"/>
            <p>If we conſider likewiſe the ſeveral other Advantages tha <hi>England</hi> receives by <hi>Ireland,</hi> for Students that come to the Univerſities and Inns of Courts, Travellers thither, the Poſt-Office, Intereſt of Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it will by a modeſt Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation appear, that the King and People of <hi>England</hi> did in thoſe Reigns receive yearly above 200000 <hi>l.</hi> clear out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> beſides the fore-mentioned Charge of the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Kingdom, and the vaſt Advantages they gain'd by the Trade thereof; from thence they were ſupplied with many Commodities uſeful and neceſſary for the carrying on of their Manufactures here, and received vaſt Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from thence; for their ſuperfluities both of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and Foreign Goods, the Computation of which I ſhall leave to thoſe that are concern'd in that Trade at this Day, or were before the War, who muſt conſequently beſt underſtand it.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſuppoſe (as we juſtly may) that <hi>Ireland</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the Circumſtances in which it was in the Year, 1686. did yield to <hi>England</hi> one Million of Pounds <hi>Sterl.</hi> in four Years: and let us compute as near as we can, the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which thoſe three grand Rebellions that have been the moſt chargable to <hi>England,</hi> has amounted to, the firſt of which broke out in the Year 1597. (till which time <hi>Ireland</hi> was never accounted a burden to <hi>England</hi>) and the exact Charge of that War, 'tis ſaid, came to 1191248 <hi>l. Sterl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Rebellion of 1641. <hi>England</hi> being embroiled in a Civil War at home (<hi>Scotland</hi> alſo being in Confuſion) was able to afford <hi>Ireland</hi> but very little Aids of Money, the Army that fought againſt the Rebels there, lived for the moſt part on their Shifts, and in conſideration of the Pay due to them, had great part of the Lands of that Country ſet out as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentures, which many of them this Day enjoy. But let us ſuppoſe that <hi>England</hi> in that War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> was at the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of one Million more.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170932:8"/>
            <p>And as for the laſt War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> I am informed, that coſt <hi>England</hi> ſomething more than two Millions, ſo that it is plain, that <hi>Ireland</hi> conſidered in the fore-mentioned Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, in the Year 1686. yielded <hi>England</hi> in twenty Years, by a very modeſt Computation, more Money than ever it coſt them to Conquer and keep it, and has more than once paid for its own purchaſe; and I may juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this part of my Diſcourſe with this Aſſertion, That <hi>Ireland</hi> next to <hi>England</hi> its ſelf, is the richeſt Jewel in the Crown, and that it hath already been very Advantageous to <hi>England,</hi> and may be much more for the future, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there be ſupported and encouraged, and the Natives kept in due ſubjection: The Truth of which, the before-mentioned Mr. <hi>W. H.</hi> has made out at large in his Book, which might have ſaved me this trouble, had it not met with the ſame Fate that this probably may, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, and neglected, becauſe it relates to <hi>Ireland,</hi> which is ſufficient to prejudice a great many againſt it. But his having done this to my Hand, is not the only Reaſon of my being ſo brief in ſpeaking to it, but becauſe it is not the main Point, which I intend to inſiſt upon. For leſt I may meet in this ſceptical Age, with ſome Perſons, that it may be as hard to induce to give Credit to this Paradox, of <hi>Ireland</hi>'s being uſeful and profitable to <hi>England,</hi> as it is to perſuade others to believe the Doctrine of the Holy Trinity, and will as much queſtion and object againſt the Truth of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtory, as ſome do againſt the Authority of the Holy Scriptures. I ſhall therefore deſire to be allowed only this one <hi>Poſtulatum</hi> or Principle to proceed upon, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſince Almighty God, when it was at his pleaſure, and he might have forborn the Creation either of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> thought fit to create them both in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of each other, and allowing that <hi>Ireland</hi> has been always a vexatious and chargable Country to <hi>England</hi> (for if the People of <hi>England</hi> will ſay, and are reſolv'd that this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170932:9"/>is, and ſhall be Truth, 'tis but Duty and good Manners in us of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſubſcribe to it) yet that it is not only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, but almoſt neceſſary, for the common Security and well being of <hi>England</hi> at home, as well as for the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their Commerce and Trade abroad, that the Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Government thereof, both in Church and State, ſhould be always in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hands, and managed according to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws there Eſtabliſh'd, and the Intereſt of this Crown therein, be conſtantly and entirely preſerved.</p>
            <p>And this is, what is, and hath been allow'd, not only by the wiſe Men of the preſent and former Ages, but by thoſe who are moſt prejudiced againſt <hi>Ireland,</hi> otherwiſe they would not have thought it worth their while to aſſert their Title to it with ſo much Vigor, and Conquer it ſo often as they have done.</p>
            <p>From this Conceſſion (which I never heard to have been refuſed by any of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation) I may deduce this very natural and undeniable Conſequence.</p>
            <p>That our moſt Wiſe and Gracious King, and the Grand Council of this Nation, the Two Houſes of Parliament, would be ſo far from Enacting or Conſenting to any thing that may prove apparently prejudicial to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in that Kingdom, which they have ſo lately, and at ſo dear a Price re-gain'd and re eſtabliſh'd, and which being violated, muſt produce ſome evil Effects even to this Kingdom, that they cannot look favourably upon any that would impoſe ſuch Advice upon them, but believe them either to be (at leaſt) ignorant of the Conſtitution of that Country, or to act out of a Principle which I don't think convenient to mention.</p>
            <p>It ſhall therefore be my Province, upon this Occaſion, humbly to repreſent, how Dangerous (I apprehend) the Conſequences of ſuch a Law as is mentioned in my Title Page, will, in all probability, prove to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170932:9"/>and the Eſtabliſh'd Church of that Nation, and only to offer to the Conſideration of the Wiſe Men of <hi>England,</hi> whether they may not in ſome time, ſeverely affect this Kingdom, tho' the Prejudice be immediately to <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I may with the greater perſpicuity and plainneſs accompliſh the ſame, 'twill be uſeful to take Notice, that that Nation conſiſts principally of three ſeveral kinds of People, whoſe Intereſts and Dependencies are very different from each other.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay ſomething of them in particular, and endeavour to ſhew how far this Law if enacted, will affect each of them; and if I demonſtrate that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Party are like to be the only ſufferers thereby, I hope I ſhall gain my Point, and that the Wiſdom of <hi>England</hi> will not think con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to do any thing that may be ruinous or prejudicial to that Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall begin with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of Popiſh <hi>Engliſh</hi> Families, as well as of the ancient Natives of that Kingdom, in which ſenſe I deſire to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood all along, when I mention the <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already hinted how vexatious and troubleſom they have been to <hi>England</hi> ever ſince the Reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, how vigorouſly they have at ſeveral times, endeavour'd to caſt off the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Yoak, and how Bloody their Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions and Maſſacres have been. And 'tis certain, that all ſuch of them as have been diſpoſſeſſed of their Eſtates, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſince the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, were turn'd out of them, by reaſon of their conſtant oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to, and uneaſineſs under the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, with which ('tis apparent) they have believ'd their Intereſt to be wholly inconſiſtent; or it cannot be imagined they would have made ſo many violent Efforts to extricate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from it: I need not therefore give my ſelf, or thoſe to whoſe hands theſe Papers ſhall come, any further trouble, by producing Arguments to prove the Dependance and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170932:10"/>Hopes of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts to be very oppoſite to thoſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Country, for if their Intereſts be ſo, this muſt of courſe be allow'd.</p>
            <p>And this they have in the late War evidently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to the World: For when the Emperor, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and moſt of the other Roman Catholick Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> were in League with his Majeſty of <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> the Pope himſelf being rather a Friend, than an Enemy; and ſuch of thoſe Princes as did not aſſiſt us againſt <hi>France,</hi> were all Neuters, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> only, with ſome ſmall aſſiſtance from <hi>France,</hi> maintain'd a brisk and vigorous War againſt us, and did indeed make a ſtronger oppoſition to the Arms of <hi>England,</hi> than we might imagine it were poſſible for them to do, if we conſider either the Condition in which they are now, (being unhorſed, and diſarm'd of all manner of Weapons of War) or the Circumſtances in which they were in any time ſince the Reſtoration of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. till the laſt part of his Reign, when by the great Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they had (by the D. of <hi>York</hi>'s means) from the Court of <hi>England,</hi> they began to ſeem formidable to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of <hi>Ireland.</hi> So that, I think I have made it evident, that as they believe the Extirpation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of that Country would be their greateſt Intereſt, and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ſo they have chiefly depended upon the <hi>French,</hi> and by them expected the accompliſhment of that great Deſign.</p>
            <p>Not that I will ſay that they have naturally a greater Affection for the <hi>French</hi> than any other Nation, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have, for ſome Years, eſteem'd the <hi>French</hi> King to be the moſt powerful and the moſt Ambitious Monarch of <hi>Europe,</hi> of the Romiſh perſwaſion; and conſequently the moſt likely to attempt the Expulſion of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> out of that Country, and (as they fondly imagined) to reſtore them to their pretended ancient Eſtates and Liberties; which is the ſame reaſon that induced them to be ſo fond of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170932:10"/>
            <p>And notwithſtanding that there have been, all along the War, conſiderable Numbers of thoſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts in the <hi>French</hi> ſervice, many of which remain there this very day, and the Ruins of Demoliſhed Towns, and Fortreſſes in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the vaſt heaps of the Bones of Slaughtered Men, which are to be ſeen in many parts of that Kingdom, are but too Freſh, and Senſible Monuments of their Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and cannot when we ſee them, but make us Reflect upon their Behaviour towards us, and remember how few years have paſſed ſince they were by downright Dint of Sword beaten into good Manners; I ſay notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all theſe things, I have been very well aſſured that long before the Concluſion of the Peace, they have made application to the Emperor, K. of <hi>Spain</hi> and other Roman Catholick Princes, that they might Intercede for them to the K. of <hi>England,</hi> as being poor Perſecuted Catholicks; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not left in a Poſture of running into another Rebellion, and Cutting of Throats at pleaſure.</p>
            <p>And, to my certain knowledge, they had <hi>September</hi> laſt their Agents or Plenipotentiaries (as ſome ſtile them) in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and have the confidence to tell us, that they were never ſo happy as under an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and that our preſent King has been gracious to them beyond expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſo far, they are in the right, and ſpeak Truth, whether they believe it or no; but they do alſo endeavour to make us believe, that moſt of any Note among them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken the Oath of Fidelity, they are now true Friends to King <hi>William</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and we know very well that Oaths have been ever ſuch Sacred Tyes, as they could not break through, but have obſerv'd them, as invfoiably, as a certain Friend of theirs, (who was always Fam'd for being nicely juſt to his word) did perform his repeated Oaths and Promiſes of Preſerving the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Governing theſe Kingdoms according to the Laws then Eſtabliſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170932:11"/>
            <p>But to lay any ſtreſs upon their aſſeverations to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is ſo grand a contradiction to Common Senſe and Experience, that reaſon can never admit it, nor Mankind be ſo far Impoſed upon, as that they ſhould expect the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of any thing of this kind from them, 'tis altogether as reaſonable to imagine, that thoſe Creatures which are called Tame Wolves, when let loofe, will abſtain from their Prey and not fall upon the Flocks and Herds, nor Foxes upon the Poultry, tis as reaſonable (I ſay) to believe this, as that <hi>Iriſh</hi> Men in power will preſerve; and not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to extirpate the Proteſtant Race out of that Country, and for my part, I ſhall ſcarce ever be convinced, but that the Character is very applicable to them which <hi>Hippolitus</hi> gives his Hunts man of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Dogs
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>— Spartanos</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Genus eſt audax avidum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſerae)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nodo cautus propiore liga.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> which according to my Interpretation is as follows, That 'tis a Turbulent ungovernable Generation, greedy of Blood, and never in good order, but when tied up, or cloſe coupled.</p>
            <p>If theſe be the People which the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> propoſe to keep in low circumſtances, they are very much in the right, for that Generation never becomes Rich or Powerful but they grow Troubleſome and Uneaſie, and are ready to joyn with any Popiſh Prince, that will aſſiſt them againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, who can never be too jealous, or careful to prevent their being in a condition, to repeat thoſe Villanies which they have ſo often and ſo lately acted againſt the Proteſtants of that Kingdom, and conſequently of putting <hi>England</hi> to any further Charge or Trouble in the Reduction of them.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170932:11"/>
            <p>There may be ſeveral particular methods propoſed for weakning that Intereſt, and incapacitating them of being any further troubleſome to <hi>England,</hi> ſuch as Baniſhing their Prieſts and Fryars; taking care to have their Children, or the greater part of them, educated in the Principles of the Proteſtant Religion, as the <hi>French</hi> do, to have thoſe of the Proteſtants in their Country, brought up to Popery. The prohibiting of Papiſts by Law to purchaſe any Lands or Freeholds in that Kingdom, and ſo forth.</p>
            <p>But if the Government of <hi>England</hi> would think conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to have Parliaments more frequently call'd in <hi>Ireland</hi> than they uſually have been, eſpecially in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. who never called one from the time of the Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Country, to the day of his Death, which without diſpute, gave the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts great opportunities of growing upon us, and being in a Condition of giving <hi>England</hi> ſuch vigorous Oppoſition, as they did in the late War; whether his deſign in that omiſſion, was to give that People thoſe opportunities or no, I ſhall not determine; but am confident, that if Parliaments were frequently call'd there, and the management of Affairs were, in ſome meaſure, left to their diſcretion, there would be ſuch pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and effectual courſes taken for ſuppreſſing the Natives of that Country, as would for ever prevent their being miſchievous or uneaſie to <hi>England;</hi> and 'tis certain that there is nothing which the conſidering and cunning Men among them, do dread more: but have had in all former Reigns, the Intereſt in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Court, to prevent it.</p>
            <p>By this means, of frequent Parliaments, and allowing the freedom of Trade, in ſome meaſure, to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Country, it would in a few Years appear, that <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is of greater advantage to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> than any thing they ever added to their Dominions, of which the Kings of <hi>England</hi> would be very ſenſible by the vaſt Revenues that would accrue to them; and this without prejudice to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170932:12"/>the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Commodities out-ſell thoſe of <hi>Ireland</hi> in all Foreign Markets; and conſidering that the Traders of <hi>Ireland</hi> lie already under ſuch Reſtrictions, that 'tis impoſſible they ſhould ever injure <hi>England,</hi> either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to its Manufactures at home, or its Commerce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; tho' there are ſome of that unſatiable Temper, that they think whatever the poor <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> do gain by their Induſtry and the bleſſing of God upon their Endeavours, to be juſt ſo much loſt out of their own Treaſures.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid ſomething of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Natives in general, I come now to their Commerce and manner of living, and how far ſuch a Law if enacted, will affect them.</p>
            <p>Tho' it is not to be doubted, but that many more of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious ſort of them, are fallen into Trade, in imitation of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> yet they are no farther concern'd in the Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Manufactures, than in buying (from the Proteſtant Tradeſmen) ſome ſmall quantities of them for their own uſe, and ſome perhaps to Tranſport by way of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize into other Countries. Nor are the Gentry or the better ſort of them much addicted to the keeping of Flocks, or raiſing Sheep; for ſuch of them as are poſſeſſed of any conſiderable quantities of Land, eſpecially if they be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Families, think themſelves above any buſineſs of that kind, or at leaſt never mind it, but live after a careleſs and prodigal way, pleaſing themſelves with a great company of Followers, Servants and Tenants (the laſt of which are in the nature of <hi>Villains</hi> to them) and ſo that they have but a ſufficient number of Sheep for their own uſe, do not much care, (nor indeed underſtand how) to propagate them. Sometimes where their Women are extrordinary Houſewives (which is rare among 'em) they make Frize and ordinary Linnen for the uſe of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, this is all the Manufacture they are concern'd in, and indeed is ſcarce worth mentioning.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170932:12"/>
            <p>But leſt it ſhould be imagined that the Generality of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> may be further concern'd in the Manufacture of that Kingdom, 'twill not be amiſs to give an Account of their Commerce and manner of Living; and there are two De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of them; the firſt is a kind of People that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Gentlemen, and Old Proprietors, and hope at one time or other to be reſtored to their ancient Eſtates, and the Number of this kind of Men is very conſiderable; for in the late War when they were, by virtue of the Act of Repeal, reſtored to their diminutive Eſtates, there were many of them that could not claim above 12, ſome not above 10, and other 6 Acres of Land, 50 or 60 Acres were large Fortunes among them; for it was a Cuſtom among moſt of the ancient <hi>Iriſh,</hi> to make an equal divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend of whatever Lands they purchaſed among all their Sons, which is the true reaſon, that there are ſo many of thoſe People in that Country, and which next to their Prieſts and Fryars are the Perſons that, of the whole <hi>Iriſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are moſt dangerous and vexatious to the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> for they think themſelves injured Perſons, being (as they ſay) unjuſtly diſpoſſeſſed of their Eſtates; thoſe ſmall Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etors being excluded by the Act of Settlement paſſed in that Kingdom after the Wars of 41.</p>
            <p>They are generally careful to procure ſome kind of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their Children, whoſe Accompliſhments are chiefly the ſpeaking of <hi>Latin,</hi> Writing tolerably well, and Playing on the Harp; they think themſelves too much Gentlemen to put their Sons to Trades, or breed them up to any thing that is Laborious, which is what they never betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to, but ſometimes walk about with their Snuſh-horns, enquiring for News; heretofore, concerning the <hi>French</hi> King and his Succeſſes againſt the Confederates, but now (I ſuppoſe) their Enquiries will be concerning the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> what kind of Spark he is like to prove, and whether they may expect ever by his means to be reſtored to their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170932:13"/>Eſtates; at other times they ſmoak Tobacco by their Fire ſides, or if the Weather be warm, Sleep, or Lowze them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Hedges, and ſpend the reſt of their time after ſome lazy and fruitleſs manner; but they are always in a readineſs upon the leaſt Commotion, to joyn the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>England,</hi> and by the aſſiſtance of their Clergy, do compel the poor ignorant Common-People to follow them to all the Miſchiefs imaginable, giving themſelves the Titles of Colonels, Captains, and what other Officers they think convenient, according to the Numbers they can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble.</p>
            <p>But it will now be convenient to give ſome ſhort account of thoſe other poor common <hi>Iriſh,</hi> their Commerce and manner of Living. They are a People of ſo tame and coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Diſpoſition, that were they not actuated by their Gentry and Clergy, and they were in never ſo great a Tumult, did the <hi>Engliſh</hi> but appear to them with their Cudgels and Scourges only, they would undoubtedly betake themſelves to their ſeveral Labours and Employments, which being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, it will appear how far they are concern'd in the Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Manufactures of that Kingdom; ſuch of them as live in the plain and fertile parts of the Country, are generally Slaves to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or to their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Landlords, and live by their daily Labour, working for 3<hi>d.</hi> and in ſome places 4<hi>d.</hi> a Day and their Dinner, their Stock is generally a Cow or two, ſome Goats, and perhaps ſix or eight ſmall <hi>Iriſh</hi> Sheep, which they clip twice a Year, and convert the Wool into coarſe Frize to cover their Nakedneſs, the ſame Cloaths ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them commonly both for wearing by Day, and for Bed cloaths by Night; when the Lambs of their few Sheep do fall, they preſerve ſome ſmall part of them to keep up their Number, and thoſe they half ſtarve for lucre of the Milk, the reſt they ſell in the Markets at 6<hi>d.</hi> or 8<hi>d.</hi> a piece; and this is what is known to all thoſe who have had the leaſt abode or acquaintance in thoſe Parts of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170932:13"/>Kingdom where the greateſt Numbers of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Inhabit. The only conſiderable Manufacture that I have ſeen or heard of among them, are thoſe great quantities of coarſe Linnen, Yarn, which are tranſported into <hi>Briſtol, Biddiford, Liver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole</hi> and other Parts of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now a Law of this kind would be ſo far from being a Diſcouragement to that People of which I am treating, <hi>viz.</hi> the vulgar <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that it would be a very great Obligation laid upon them; For before the late War in that Kingdom, the Flocks were grown ſo numerous in all the plain Parts of the Country, that the vulgar <hi>Iriſh</hi> were driven for the moſt part into the mountainous and woody Parts of the Kingdom, except ſuch as were neceſſary for ſome Services, in which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for want of others, were forced to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them: Inſomuch, that I have my ſelf very frequently heard them curſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sheep with all the bitterneſs and rancor imaginable; and pray to God, <hi>That he would ſend a Rot or a Plague among the Sheep, that the poor of the Country might have greater ſcopes of Ground for tillage,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And this was the true Reaſon, that in the beginning of the late War they made ſuch barbarous Havock of that kind of Cattel more than any other, killing hundreds of them in the Fields, when they had occaſion for the Fleſh but of a very few, which did not a little contribute in two or three Years time, to occaſion ſo great a Scarcity in that plentiful Kingdom, that if the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army (eſpecially when driven over the <hi>Shannon</hi>) had not been plentifully reliev'd from <hi>France,</hi> a great many of the Country muſt have ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably periſhed by Famine.</p>
            <p>So that 'tis a grand miſtake to think that the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of them are Richer now than ever; there were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly a great many particular Perſons among them, who by being more eminent Rapparees than others, and being concern'd in ſeizing the Proteſtants Goods, have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170932:14"/>made conſiderable Fortunes in the late Troubles, ſome of which have Tranſported themſelves and their Effects into <hi>France,</hi> and others under the ſubterfuge of the Articles of <hi>Lymerick, Galway,</hi> &amp;c. have ſheltered themſelves from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Juſtice, and live ſplendidly and ſecurely upon the Spoils of ruined Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in general are a kind of People that cannot keep Riches by them, for tho' the Gentry of them had ever ſo great Rents coming into them, they do uſually ſpend their half Year's income, in leſs than three Months, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning partly in Debt for the remainder of the time, and partly ſpunging on their Neighbours and Tenants, which latter was look'd upon to be ſo heavy a Burden to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, that there has been an Act of Parliament paſſed againſt <hi>Coſherers</hi> or <hi>Smell-Feaſts</hi> in that Kingdom: and indeed their extravagance, and ill management are the true Reaſons why the Wine-Merchants, and other Traders among them have either purchaſed, or lent Money on the Eſtates of moſt of the antient <hi>Iriſh</hi> Families.</p>
            <p>And as for the univerſal Plunder which the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army the Rapparees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> took from the Proteſtants before, and in the late War, they were no ſooner Maſters of any part of it, but it was immediately deſtroyed: when they drove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way an Herd of Cattel (which was common with them) they never ceaſed ſlaughtering both Fat and Lean, till they had conſumed all, neglecting their Potato's and other ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Food, to which they had been accuſtom'd: when they plundered a Houſe, they ſhaked the Feathers out of the Beds into the Streets or High ways, and made Sacks of the Ticking to carry away the other Goods; they cut the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Hangings, Linnen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into Cloaths; both Men and Women neglecting all manner of Work, and living upon Spoil and Rapine, which was the means by which that Country was reduced to that miſerable Condition in which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army found it when they reduced it; and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170932:14"/>yet I doubt not but if the Lands of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were to be ſold, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> might ſoon be furniſhed with Money from abroad to purchaſe them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In order to make good my general Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> are like to be the only Sufferers, by the paſſing a Law purſuant to the <hi>Exon.</hi> Petition I cannot avoid ſaying ſomething of another ſort of People that Inhabit great part of that Kingdom, their Intereſt, Commerce and Dependance, and theſe are the <hi>Scotch</hi> Diſſenters or Presbyterians (as they call Themſelves) of that Nation, as in conjunction with that Party in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who have lately run down Epiſcopacy there.</p>
            <p>For I muſt here declare to the World, that I intend no ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral national Reflection, knowing that thô the Kirk of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be now Triumphant, yet there are ſtill, both there and in <hi>Ireland.</hi> the remains of the Church of <hi>Scots,</hi> which (I hope) God will in his own good Time repair and beautifie and that there are a great many Men of Learning and VViſdom, Honour and Bravery of that Nation, concerned in all man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of Stations in theſe three Kingdoms, in the Church, the Army and the Commonwealth, between whom and our ſelves I do not think it reaſonable nor fair to make any diſtinction, ſince we profeſs the ſame Faith, have been all along embarqued in the ſame common Cauſe, and (Thanks be to God) have to very good purpoſe co-operated towards the attainment of the ſame End, which is the ſecurity of our Religion and Properties, and that both may be Eſtabliſhed upon Firm and Laſting Foundations in oppoſition to all manner of Enemies, according to the Antient and known Laws of theſe His Majeſty's Dominions.</p>
            <p>And becauſe 'tis uſual with that Party to interpret all things which are ſaid (upon any occaſion whatſoever) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliging to them as Reflections upon the Reformed Churches abroad, I do here ſolemnly profeſs, that I have a very great eſteem for thoſe Churches, and have not the leaſt intention
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170932:15"/>of ſaying any thing that may give them the leaſt Offence; being very ſenſible, that they are ſo far from having an ill opinion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they are very well ſatisfied with her Doctrines, and, if we may believe ſome Learned Men among them (as I think in Reaſon and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we ought to do) they tell us, that if their Biſhops would have joyn'd with them in the Reformation, they would not have rejected an Order ſo Ancient and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal in the Chriſtian Church: But ſince their Biſhops were ſo tied to their Temporal Intereſts that they would not bear a part in that great Work, the Presbytery thought themſelves obliged in Conſcience to renounce the groſs Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries, and Superſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe Declarations being made, it will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, who theſe are, whoſe Intereſts and Dependance I am to ſhew, are different from thoſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland:</hi> And tho' we have too ſevere an Inſtance, and Proof, in the late Revolution in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they are not ſhye either in doing, or ſaying any thing that may conduce to the promotion of their Old Cauſe and Intereſt; yet I ſhall endeavour to expreſs my ſelf in as ſoft and inoffenſive Terms as I can, without doing wrong to the Subject in hand.</p>
            <p>For it is not my purpoſe, at this time, to enter into a Controverſie with them concerning Religion, but to let them know only, that I would not willingly have them our Maſters, or that it ſhould ever lye in their powers to deal with the Eſtabliſh'd Church of <hi>Ireland</hi> as they did with that of <hi>Scotland;</hi> for there are a great many living Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Cruelties and Barbarities, eſpecially to the poor Clergy of that Church, whom they were not ſatisfied by turning out of their Churches and Livings, without the leaſt proviſion for their Families; nor yet, with pillaging and burning their Houſes, ſtripping and abuſing their Wives and Children in many places, but offered ſuch indignities to their Perſons, as were not offered to the Perſons of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170932:15"/>Proteſtant Clergy that ſtayed in <hi>Ireland</hi> during the late War in that Kingdom; not that I have a favourable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Vertue and Goodneſs of the Papiſts of <hi>Ireland</hi> in general; for I do not doubt, but they would have out as many Throats as they did in 41. had not the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Perſons among their Chiefs foreſeen, that in all probability they muſt very ſoon be call'd to an Account for it; for many of them have ſince the late War upon the leaſt diſguſt, curſed themſelves, that they left it in the power of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that ſtay'd among them ever to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure them; nor had it ſeem'd ſtrange to us, if they had proceeded to a Maſſacre, it being no more than a repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their former Villanies, and what we expected from them.</p>
            <p>But it was wonderfully ſurprizing to us, to ſee a great many of the Epiſcopal Clergy of <hi>Scotland</hi> come into this Kingdom for ſhelter, in a more miſerable Condition (if 'twere poſſible) from their own Country-men, Relations and Brethren (who call themſelves Proteſtants, and have been the great Champions for Liberty of Conſcience, and Declaimers againſt Perſecution) than of <hi>Ireland</hi> did, much about the ſame time, from their inveterate, irreconcilable Enemies the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> the latter being driven away by force and violence, and in ſure hope of a quick and happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their own Country, but the former by Law with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt proſpect of Reſtauration, which is the moſt diſmal Circumſtance that ever attended any Affliction, and which renders the Damn'd themſelves compleatly miſerable.</p>
            <p>I need not here trouble the Reader with the repetition of thoſe inhumane Cruelties which were exerciſed on that poor Clergy; for this Nation has had ſufficient Proofs and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of them, not only in print, but from the Mouths of a great many, who bore a part in thoſe Sufferings. I ſhall therefore only give ſome few Inſtances of the Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome of thoſe People, to which I was an eye-witneſs in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170932:16"/>
               <hi>Ireland.</hi> If I mention any other paſſage, it ſhall be ſuch as ſhall plainly ſhew, what uſage we muſt expect from that Nation, ſhould they ever be in a condition of Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering over us. And</p>
            <p>Firſt. Being in <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> in the beginning of the Year 1690. a little before his Majeſty Landed there, one of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains of the Army walking on the Key of that Town in his Gown, was ſpied by a parcel of Demi-Tarrs in blue Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, who came in a Boat from <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſell Oatmeal, and Eggs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they were ſo tranſported with Rage at the ſight of him, that not conſidering that they were not in <hi>Scotland</hi> (where they had been accuſtomed to uſe ſuch Men ill, and were accounted Religious and Zealous in ſo doing) they began without more ado to revile him, and belch out, I know not how many <hi>Scotch</hi> Curſes and opprobrious words againſt him, and would in all probability have offer'd him ſome Violence, had they not been ſoon made to know, by ſome Gentlemen that were near the place, that they were not in their own Country, where an Epiſcopal Clergy-man, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſhould he appear in his proper Habit, muſt expect to be uſed, as the Poet ſays the Owl is, when ſhe happens to appear by Day light:
<q>—<hi>à cunctis expellitur aethere toto.</hi>
                  <bibl>Ovid. Met.</bibl>
               </q> All the reſt of the Birds fall foul upon her, as a Bird of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> Immediately after this happened, I met a Gentleman of very good Senſe and Learning, and (I'm very well ſatisfied) of great Integrity, who was Chaplain to a <hi>Daniſh</hi> Regiment of Horſe; he aſſured me, that being commanded by his Superiors in <hi>Denmark,</hi> to fit himſelf with the ſame Habit with the Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> as ſoon as he ſhould come into our King's Dominions; and having done ſo at <hi>York,</hi> was ſoon after obliged to march with that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170932:16"/>Regiment to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> where he no ſooner appear'd in a Gown, but he was ſurprized at the Mobs flocking about him in great numbers, he perceiv'd that they began to come very near him, and to take up Dirt, and whatever elſe the Street afforded, to throw at him; being in ſome conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not knowing what they meant, unleſs it were becauſe they had diſcovered him to be a Stranger, not in the leaſt imagining that the Gown could be ſo very offenſive to them, he made what haſt he could to ſome Perſons that look'd like Gentlemen, who were walking towards him, whom he found ſmiling, and pleaſed at the Rabbles beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to him: He told them, that it was not the Cuſtom of his Country to uſe Strangers after that inhumane manner, and that he little expected it, having come ſo far to ſerve the King of <hi>England;</hi> but that ſince the Gentlemen encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the other in ſo great a piece of Rudeneſs, he would apply to the Army with which he came for ſatisfaction for ſo great an Affront; whereupon finding him to be a Foreigner, they diſpers'd the Mobb and begg'd his pardon, telling him that they thought he was an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miniſter, or they would have reſcued him ſooner: To which he replied, That he therefore thought them the greater Barbarians; and that if they uſed their Neighbours after that unchriſtian manner; he was the leſs concern'd for his Abuſe, and had no reaſon to expect either Civility, or Good-manners from them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. Another Inſtance of this kind, to which I was eye-witneſs, is as follows; In a few days after that Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman told me this Paſſage, there were two Clergy-men walking in their Gowns upon the Bridge of <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> who were alſo Chaplains in the Army, to whom I ſaw one go (who counted himſelf a topping Gentleman in the North of <hi>Ireland</hi>) and take up the Skirt of one of the Gowns in a gibing manner, telling them in a deriding Tone, and in broad <hi>Scotch</hi> (tho' 'twas not his uſual Dialect) that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchops were put down in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170932:17"/>
            <p>Fourthly. I have heard ſeveral of the vulgar <hi>Scotch</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> belonging to the Army ſay, That when the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts were Conquer'd, they hoped the Biſhops (meaning the Epiſcopal Party) ſhould be the next againſt whom they ſhould Fight, and I was credibly inform'd, that it was a frequent Expreſſion among the Commonalty of them.</p>
            <p>Theſe two laſt Inſtances I produce, to ſhew that this furious Zeal, and Spirit of Perſecution, is not peculiar to thoſe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but that their Friends in <hi>Ireland</hi> have their portion of the ſame: which might be further proved by ſeveral particulars, were it neceſſary to the main Deſign and Matter in hand.</p>
            <p>Fifthly. But there is one Inſtance more, to which tho' I was not an eye-witneſs, yet I received the Account from thoſe whoſe Veracity I do not at all queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſome poor Gentlewomen who, about the beginning of the Siege of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> were ſent by their Husbands (who ſtay'd behind them in that Service) to <hi>Scotland</hi> for ſecurity, when they were Landed there with heavy Hearts, and probably not very much in their Purſes, yet they found within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſome ſmall degrees of Satisfaction and Eaſe ariſing from the conſideration of their being ſafely Landed in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Country, out of the noiſe of continual Allarums, and the Dangers and Fears occaſioned by the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of a powerful Enemy, to which for ſome time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had been ſubject: And there they had for ſome time, ſuch a Reception as might be reaſonably expected in that Country, till partly by their own unwary Diſcourſe, but chiefly by the Malice and Treachery of ſome of their Presbyterian Neighbours that went over about the ſame time, they were diſcovered to be ſuch as made uſe of that horrid Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Common-Prayer;</hi> and (which was worſt of all) that one of them was the Wife of a Curate, which is the Title they have for our Miniſters; upon which Diſcovery, the poor Gentlewomen were turned out of doors, with as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170932:17"/>much precipitation, and violence, as if they had eſcaped from a City where the Plague raged, or that ſome Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from Heaven muſt inevitably fall upon the Houſe that ſhould harbour them; and could have neither Meat, Drink, nor Lodging for their Money (notwithſtanding that Coin is ſo well beloved by the Inhabitants of that Country) but were forced to walk further, where being leſs known, they were more regarded, and were very glad that they eſcaped without Violence.</p>
            <p>And now, methinks, they that had ſo lately cried out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Perſecution on account of Religion, and the barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Penal Laws, as they did in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. and the late King <hi>James</hi> alſo, till thoſe Managers which led that unfortunate Prince by the Noſe, began to think it Policy, to careſs them, and bring them to ſide with his Intereſt againſt the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Methinks (I ſay) they ſhould not have made ſuch ſevere applications of a Law of that kind, as they did in their own Country; and at a juncture of time, when the King and People of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> were engaged, not only in a Foreign War againſt <hi>France,</hi> but in another bloody War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and a third in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not ſay, that this proceeding againſt the Epiſcopal Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> at that time, looked like an Impoſition upon the Neceſſities of <hi>England;</hi> but the World muſt judge the taking that Advantage, to be ungenerous; and that it was as much, as if they had ſaid, that ſince their Aſſiſtance was required againſt the Common Enemy, the extirpation of Epiſcopacy was the recompence they expected, and muſt have, in conſideration of their Services.</p>
            <p>And tho' they could not ſay, when they were reſolv'd to ruin that Church, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did when they were bent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Crucifixion of our Saviour, <hi>We have a Law among us, and by that Law he ought to die;</hi> yet they enacted, among themſelves, a Law to that purpoſe, which occaſioned a great
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170932:18"/>many to ſide with <hi>Dundee,</hi> and oppoſed His Majeſty's Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in that Kingdom, to the utmoſt of their Power, who longed earneſtly for this happy Revolution, and expected thereby to be delivered from the then imminent Danger of Slavery and Popery, not thinking that they ſhould fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another no leſs cruel Bondage.</p>
            <p>And indeed, this proceeding might have turned the Hearts of a great many more, in that Nation, againſt the Intereſt of His preſent Majeſty and the People of <hi>England;</hi> had not thoſe poor Men wiſely conſidered, that it was the Act of their own bigotted Country-men, and therefore inſtead of taking up Arms againſt <hi>England,</hi> they fled hither in great Numbers, for Succour and Protection; which may be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteem'd to be one remarkable Link in that Chain of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing Providences, which attended His Sacred Majeſty in reſcuing theſe Nations from Tyranny and Miſery: for ſince the great Principle of Self-preſervation was never more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally acknowledged, than at this Day; we muſt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the deſires of Liberty and Property to be peculiar to our ſelves alone: and had the Epiſcopal Party in <hi>Scotland</hi> joyn'd entirely with our Enemies, and the Providence of God had not appeared ſo viſibly in the Affairs of <hi>Ireland;</hi> but that <hi>Enniskillin</hi> and <hi>Londonderry</hi> had been taken by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Army, or a conſiderable part of it, been tranſported into <hi>Scotland:</hi> it might have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the face of Affairs, been of fatal Conſequence to theſe Nations, and an univerſal prejudice to all the Confederate Princes of <hi>Europe.</hi> And whether the War carried on by <hi>Dundee</hi> and his Accomplices, has been prejudicial or charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the People of <hi>England,</hi> is a point which I ſhall leave to their own determination.</p>
            <p>But that I may obviate an Objection which (I am ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive) may here be raiſed, I do confeſs that the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> as well of <hi>Ireland</hi> as <hi>Scotland,</hi> were in the late War active and aſſiſting in the ſuppreſſion of the Enemies of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170932:18"/>
               <hi>England;</hi> and do highly approve their Prudence and Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, in rejecting thoſe Conditions which were in the latter part of the late Reign offered them by the Papiſts, from whom they very well knew, they were to expect no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of performance, longer than they ſerved their Turn; and do think it was wiſely ſaid by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Diſſenting Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, that the Papiſts would make ſcaffolding of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, to pull down the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that when the Work ſhould be finiſhed, that kind of Lumber would be thought fit for nothing but to be thrown into the Fire.</p>
            <p>Nor do I envy them the free Exerciſe of their Religion, and the other Priviledges which they enjoy upon theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts: and do hope they are now fully convinced that the Cruelties which in the two laſt Reigns, were exerciſed upon them, and they charged upon the Church of <hi>England;</hi> I hope (I ſay) that they are now abundantly convinced, that thoſe bitter Waters proceeded from another Spring, ſince it is apparent to the World that thoſe Princes were acted by Popiſh Emiſſaries, who were at the bottom of their Councils.</p>
            <p>I am alſo very much of the Opinion of the before-mentioned Mr. <hi>W. H. That all Proteſtants ought to be united againſt the Common Enemy;</hi> and ſhould think it a great Happineſs, they could, by any fair means be brought to ſo Heavenly a Temper; and do deſire they will, in order thereto, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider (if as he ſays <hi>they differ only from us on account of a few unneceſſary Ceremonies.</hi>) how great a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief it is, on ſuch ſlight Grounds, to ſeparate from a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church eſtabliſhed by Law in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> reſpected, beloved, and honoured by all the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches abroad, and againſt which, they can frame no other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Objection.</p>
            <p>But as I have ſaid already, 'tis not my Buſineſs at this time to run into Religious Controverſies, but to contribute
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170932:19"/>my ſmall Endeavours towards the Security of that Church, and the Proſperity of that Body of Men, of which I profeſs my ſelf to be a Member; and tho' an inconſiderable one, yet ſuch as muſt partake both in the Indolence and Sufferings of the whole.</p>
            <p>There may perhaps be ſome in the World, who will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to admire at me, that I ſhould be troubled with the thoughts of Sickneſs and Miſery, in Health and Proſperity! that I ſhould be diſturbed by the Conſideration of foul Weather, when the Heavens ſmile, and all Nature is gay and pleaſant! that I ſhould talk of the Subverſion and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of a Church, that is but juſt delivered from her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the hands of them that hate Her, and reſtored to Peace and Proſperity; that is countenanced by the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſupported by the Laws of that Country! they will ſay, that it were enough for me to write after this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy manner, if we were actually Sufferers, and labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under ſome heavy Calamity or Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>Indeed this Objection muſt be allowed to be very ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, had we not too too clear a proſpect of an alteration, if means be not uſed in time to prevent it; they may envy the preſent Serenity of our Clime, our Health, and the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Conſtitution, of which Bleſſings, tho' we be very ſenſible, and do thank God for them; yet we cannot but take notice of thoſe Clouds that we ſee thicken at a diſtance, which may probably break out upon us (in the midſt of our Summer) in Hail and Thunder: And when we perceive thoſe Symptoms about us, which are but too ſure Prognoſticks of an approaching Diſtemper, we think it highly reaſonable to make uſe of all proper means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen our next Neighbouring Church ruined by Men void of Remorſe or Pity; and that the very ſame, or their Brethren in <hi>Ireland</hi> have made conſiderable advances towards doing the ſame thing there ſince the late War, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170932:19"/>daily footing in all the Cities, Corporations, and Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in that Kingdom, ſo far that in the moſt conſiderable of them, they have been Mayors, Sheriffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that out of Decency and Reſpect to the Government, they have waited on the Sword to Church on <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning in their Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, yet they uſually ſculked in the Afternoon to a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, which is a common thing in the <hi>North,</hi> and ſome other Parts of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Men of this diſſembling Principle, may prove tolerable Magiſtrates, whilſt they are bounded by Law, aw'd by the Chief Government of the Nation, and remain in the Stations which they now are; but when they come to be Knights and Burgeſſes in Parliament (as in proceſs of time they are like to be) and the Affairs of the Church come to be debated before them, then let the ſober part of Mankind judge, what may be expected from their Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>We do therefore think it more prudential to take time by the fore-lock, and ſpeak before we are ruined, than to truſt to ſuch a bloody after-Game as has been lately repeated in that unfortunate Kingdom. For to believe that if the <hi>Scotch Presbyterians</hi> of that Country, had it in their Power, they would not uſe the Epiſcopal Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Scotland</hi> did that with them, would be as unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as to imagine, that off-ſets will not bear the ſame Flowers with the main Roots, from whence they were divided, or that Trees will produce Fruit of a different <hi>Species,</hi> by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tranſplanted from one Soil into another.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore further conſider them as a People <hi>of a different Intereſt and Dependance</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland;</hi> in their Intereſts, 'tis plain, they are link'd with their Friends in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and conſequently their main Dependance muſt alſo be upon them, whom they imitate both in their Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical and Civil Affairs, and from thence they take all their Meaſures which concern either Religion or Commerce; from thence they are furniſhed with their Clergy, and do
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170932:20"/>hold a ſtrict and conſtant Correſpondence with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The number of this People is wonderfully increaſed in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince the Battel of the <hi>Boyne,</hi> in the Year 1690. for by common Computation, above Fourſcore Thouſand Families of them have ſince that time, tranſplanted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from <hi>Scotland</hi> into that Kingdom; and they are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed not only of almoſt the whole Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> but are in great numbers, in many Parts of the other Provinces, even in the Counties of <hi>Cork, Kerry,</hi> and <hi>Limerick,</hi> which are that Part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that lies moſt remote from <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and in thoſe Counties which were the Frontiers in the Years 1690 and 1691. and were waſted by both Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, there are many more of this People to be ſeen than of any other Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>As for their Commerce, 'tis certain, that many of them in the moſt conſiderable Sea-Ports of that Kingdom, are fallen into the Merchandizing Trade thereof, and by their Correſpondence with <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> have ſufficiently enrich'd themſelves.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the happy Concluſion of the Peace, has put it out of their Power to be any further injurious to the People of <hi>England</hi> upon the account of aſſiſting their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I ſhall forbear enlarging upon this Particular, and only add, that the very laſt Winter, there were ſuch vaſt Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Corn and Meal carried to the Northern Parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Scotland;</hi> that it had certainly occaſioned a Famine in that plentiful Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> had not the then Lords Juſtices thereof very timely, and prudently, by their Proclamation, prohibited the farther Exportation of thoſe Commodities.</p>
            <p>Let us now conſider this People's Manufacture, not only in the <hi>North,</hi> but other Parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where they have fixed themſelves ſince the late War, and this doth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170932:20"/>if not altogether, conſiſt in Linnen-Cloth, with which they do not only furniſh <hi>Ireland,</hi> but do frequently ſend great Quantities of it into ſeveral Parts of <hi>England.</hi> This is a Truth ſo well known to Men of Trade, and to all ſuch as have had the Opportunity of ſeeing that Country, or of having Commerce with that People, that I need not mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply words in proving it.</p>
            <p>But 'tis certain the Commonalty of them are ſo intent upon this kind of Manufacture, that the very Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and their Servants, when they return from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours abroad, ſuch as Plowing, Sowing, Fencing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do imploy themſelves by their Fire-ſides in this kind of Work, and ſit reeling of Linnen-Yarn, while the Women are buſy in Spinning; and by this Conſtancy and Diligence, that Country produces great Quantities of good Linnen yearly.</p>
            <p>But their Woollen Manufacture is ſo very inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that I may juſtly ſay, it bears no more proportion to that of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> than their Friends in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Fleet did to the Royal Navy of <hi>England</hi> ſome Years ago, when a reflecting News-monger told us in his printed Paper, That the <hi>Scotch</hi> Fleet, conſiſting of two Frigats, cruiſing off the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was taken by two <hi>French</hi> Privateers.</p>
            <p>I do indeed allow, that they make ſome ordinary Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Cloth for their own uſe; but that they are concerned in any thing that can be called a Wollen Manufacture to be tranſported into other Countries, is what (I never heard) they ſomuch as pretended.</p>
            <p>The Merchants of them (as I have ſaid of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants) do undoubtedly deal in Woollen Manufactures, which they tranſport to other Countries, but they Buy thoſe Commodities from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Kingdom, who there are the only conſiderable Manufacturers of that kind.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170932:21"/>
            <p>And from hence it may be eaſily perceived, how far the Law before mentioned (if enacted) can affect this kind of Men; the generality of them being not at all concern'd in the Matter: and tho' it may be ſome ſmall diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the Merchants of them, as well as to others that Trade that way, yet it cannot much diſoblige them, for 'twill be a great means to make them Maſters of the Lands of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Kingdom, for they are the beſt able and the likelieſt of any to purchaſe them, being by much the richeſt People in that Country, or at leaſt much richer than ever they were before.</p>
            <p>This will not appear improbable, if we conſider, that tho' they were deſpoiled by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in the beginning, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were; yet that the War at length proved vaſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to them; for Duke <hi>Schonberg</hi> having landed with the Army in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the beginning of the Year 1689. the greater part of them had the opportunity of ſettling immediately in their places of abode, became Victuallers and Suttlers to the Camp: and the Army conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing the whole Winter after the Camp of <hi>Dundalk</hi> among them, and being duly paid from <hi>England,</hi> the Inhabitants of that Province got the greater part of that Money for their Meat, Drink, and other neceſſary Commodities with which they ſupplied the Soldiers from <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and out of the Product of their own Country. And that part of the Army which was on the Frontiers that Winter, brought in conſiderable Preys of Cattel from the Enemy, which they ſold at eaſy Rates to the Inhabitants, who by this means began to have ſome ſtock on their Lands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1690. when the Army marched toward the Enemy, vaſt Numbers both of Men and Women followed from thence as Victuallers, Suttlers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and having plenty of Money purchaſed moſt of the vaſt Preys which were taken by the Army that Campaign, and drove incredible Numbers
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170932:21"/>of Cattel into <hi>Ulſter,</hi> ſo that the Winter following they were able to ſupply <hi>Dublin,</hi> and the greater part of <hi>Leinſter</hi> with Beef, Mutton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and had ſtill their Emiſſaries with the Army on the Frontiers, to buy up the Preys, which they took daily from the Enemy in great Numbers, and which generally, through want of Graſs in the Enemies Quarters were lean, and not fit for preſent Service.</p>
            <p>The Army began no ſooner to Rendezvous in the Year 1691. but their old Acquaintance were up with them again, and follow'd the ſame Trade till <hi>Galway</hi> and <hi>Limerick</hi> were Surrenderd, at which juncture having more Money, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed underſtanding the <hi>Laganeers</hi> Trade, or Scampering, better than the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they ſwept away moſt part of the Cattle of <hi>Connaught,</hi> and <hi>Munſter</hi> with them. And, to my certain knowledge, within two Months after, the Cows which they bought for 8 or 10 Shillings, were purchaſed from them by the reſt of the Kingdom at five and fifty Shillings, and ſome at three Pound a Head; by which means they got moſt of the Money, and conſequently of the Trade of the Kingdom into their hands: So that ſeveral of them that uſed before the late War to beat upon the Hoof after a Pony laden with Pedlars Goods to the Fairs and Markets of the Kingdom, are now Maſters of Ships at Sea, and Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes crammed with Merchants Goods at home.</p>
            <p>But it would be as unreaſonable to conclude from hence that the whole Country is Rich; as 'twould be to ſay, that a Man whoſe Eſtate conſiſts of three or four different Farms, and moſt of his Cattle and Tenants are crowded into one of them, that therefore his Lands were all well ſtock'd and inhabited: For indeed if this be ſaid of the reſt of the Nation, 'tis a very great miſtake, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in relation to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Country, whom I come now</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To conſider as they are a diſtinct People both from the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch,</hi> by which I mean the Proteſtant
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170932:22"/>Families of that People, who firſt ſubdued that Nation, and have from time to time, ſupported and preſerved the Intereſt and Title of <hi>England</hi> therein; never was any Rebellion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Natives, but what began with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thoſe poor <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> who were ſure to be the firſt ſufferers, being moſt feared and hated by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who give them the Title of <hi>Clanna Galda</hi> in their own Language, which ſignifies the Children or Offspring of <hi>Engliſh-men;</hi> looking upon them as their Enemies and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, that firſt ſubdued them, and now enjoy the Eſtates that they loſt, and which were granted to the others by the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> in conſideration of their Services in the ſeveral Conqueſts and Rebellions of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Provinces, and Parts thereof.</p>
            <p>To theſe muſt be added thoſe vaſt numbers of <hi>Engliſh</hi> that have more lately tranſplanted themſelves and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies into that Kingdom, and incorporated with their Friends and Country men which they found there; who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to welcome and encourage ſuch of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation as deſire to ſettle among them; that they may be thereby the better able to oppoſe the common Enemy of the People of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Intereſts they eſteem to be the ſame with their own, and conſequently they depend upon them as their conſtant Friends, to whom they are to apply in all Emergencies, as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> have done of late Years upon the <hi>French;</hi> and the <hi>Scotch</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon their Friends in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſufficient Demonſtration hereof we have had in the beginning of the late Revolution when there was ſcarce any one of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that fled hither for refuge, till the Tyranny at home was over-paſt, but could point to the Rock from whence he was hewn, give an account of the Family from whence he or his Anceſtors ſprang, and claim (as Mr. <hi>Phillips</hi> obſerves in his Book call'd <hi>The Intereſt of</hi> England <hi>in the Preſervation of</hi> Ireland) a Father, Brother, or near Kinſman.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170932:22"/>
            <p>And accordingly, we had not only a Charitable, but a Generous Proviſion made for us, each of us being enabled to live in ſome proportion, to his Degree and Quality in his own Country: till by their Treaſure, and their Blood mixed with ours, they ſettled us again on our ancient Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, reſtor'd us to our Religion, Eſtates and Liberties and gave us our Judges as at the Firſt, and our Counſellors, as at the beginning. Which ineſtimable Bleſſings we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with Joy and Satisfaction; with all imaginable Gratitude to God, and the great Inſtruments by which he perfected our Liberty; to the King and People of <hi>England;</hi> for whom we are ready (as one Man) to hazard thoſe Lives, and Fortunes, which it ſo lately coſt them dear to ſecure to us.</p>
            <p>For tho' I have had the opportunity of being acquainted with, or at leaſt knowing by their Character, moſt of the conſiderable <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants of that Kingdom, yet I have not heard of twenty <hi>Jacobites</hi> among them all, and theſe too have learn'd to be ſo in <hi>England,</hi> and (if I miſtake not) do live here for the moſt part, which they may do with greater eaſe and freedom than in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the very Papiſts dare not own themſelves to be otherwiſe, than Friends to King <hi>William,</hi> and his Government: For we have ſo lately experimented the Conſequences of a Popiſh Government, having ſmarted under thoſe Evils which only threatned <hi>England,</hi> or which (we thank God) were remov'd as ſoon as they began; that we think it as unreaſonable, that one who reſolves to live a Proteſtant, ſhould deſire that a Popiſh Prince might Rule over him; as that a Man ſhould imploy a Wolf for his Shepherd, or an Eagle to protect and ſecure a Dove-houſe: But the World ſure has had ſufficient proofs, that it is next to a meer Contradiction, that the Proteſtant Religion ſhould be cheriſhed under the Wings of Popery. Indeed ſhould I ſee that come to paſs, I ſhould think the Prophecy fulfilled one way which I never
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170932:23"/>heard it applied before, That <hi>the Lion ſhould lie down with the Lamb, and the ſucking Child play on the hole of the Aſp;</hi> But we are ſo well convinced of the Incompatibleneſs of our Religion and Popery, that in the whole Houſe of Commons in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when the Aſſociation was to be Signed, there was but one Man, or two at the moſt, that ſo much as bogled at it; and they too, in ſpight of their ſqueamiſhneſs, were obliged to do it, under the penalty of being ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully expell'd that Honourable Aſſembly: And by this Rule we may judge of the whole Body of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Nation.</p>
            <p>And I would to God that all that call themſelves Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men were ſo firmly united in their Intereſts and Affections, ſo ſenſible of the great and mighty Deliverance which has been wrought for them, when they were at the very brink of Deſtruction, and ready to be tumbled into an Abyſs of Miſery; as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> are, there would be very few or no diſaffected Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in theſe Nations, that ſhould even wiſh evil to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government, except the Papiſts, whom notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpecious pretences they may make to us, we muſt never depend upon, as true, and hearty Friends.</p>
            <p>Nor can I imagine, how it can be expected, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Country ſhould be of another Diſpoſition than that of which our ſufferings have taught us to be; for we cannot but reflect on the condition in which we were, in the latter end of the year 1687. and the beginning of (88.) when every ſtanch Proteſtant in that Nation, upon condition we could be ſure of ſuch a Deliverer, as God ſent ſoon after to theſe Kingdoms, would undoubtedly have cried out, One half of my Goods I give to the War; as <hi>Zaccheus</hi> did of his to the Poor, when he found the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this did not ſerve our turn in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I preſume, none will deny our ſufferings there, to have been much greater than the People of <hi>England:</hi> but for the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170932:23"/>further proof or illuſtration hereof, let us frame a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, between the perſonal or corporal ſufferings of thoſe which ſerv'd in the Army in that Kingdom, and abroad elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; and the loſſes which the People of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſuſtain'd in their Eſtates and Fortunes. And</p>
            <p>Firſt, There were a great many of the Army whoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers were ſo eaſie, that they were cured by Phlebotomy, and the ordinary Medicines which are uſed in common caſes; with theſe I rank thoſe alſo, whoſe wounds which they received in the War, were ſo favourable that they were brought to digeſtion, cleanſed, and heal'd up by gentle means and applications; tho' both the one and the other did perhaps loſe great part of their Blood, and Strength for a time, yet they made no great matter of it, but thought themſelves happy Men that they eſcaped ſo.</p>
            <p>And as theſe Men ſuffered in their Perſons or Bodies, ſo we ſay, comparatively, the People of <hi>England</hi> (I mean ſuch as were not Members of the Army) did in reſpect of their Eſtates and Fortunes; their Purſes bled frequently and freely, and they paid incredible Sums of Money to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the carrying on of the War: But yet they liv'd quietly in their own Country and Houſes, preſerved gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally their main Stock, and followed their lawful Callings and Affairs; which if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> could have done, it had this day been a happy and flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, tho' an Object far below either the Envy or Jealouſie of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. Another kind of Sufferers which we have ſeen in the Army during the War, are ſuch as have ſat quietly and patiently while their Limbs were amputated, and (which is more dreadful) many of them cauterized or ſeared with hot Irons, and all in hopes of preſerving their maim'd and imperfect Carcaſſes, that they might have a Being in the World, and be able to go, or halt about their Occaſions, even this being more eligible than utter Diſſolution.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170932:24"/>
            <p>To theſe Mens Condition, we may liken that of ſome few of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that is in relation to their Worldly Subſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> The Tradeſmen, Taylors, Shoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, Hatters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which continued in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and other Corporations in that Kingdom; tho' the <hi>Iriſh</hi> uſed theſe poor Men like Slaves, and gave them but what they pleaſed for their Commodities, or their Labour; yet they did not take all from them, but left them ſomething to live upon, becauſe they could not want them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. I can compare the Circumſtances of the generality of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Kingdom, the Nobility, Clergy, Gentry and Commonalty, with reſpect to their Eſtates and Fortunes, to none more aptly, than to thoſe great numbers of Men, that loſt their Lives by thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Diſtempers, that for ſome time raged in the Army; and fell in Battle by the hands of their Enemies. For I need not tell the World, that our Enemies were our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that they diſpoſſeſſed us of our Churches, Eſtates, and Houſes, and burnt many of the latter to the ground; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd the Improvements that we and our Fathers had been making ever ſince the former Settlement, almoſt through the whole Country; and made us as poor and miſerable as they could. And tho' (thanks be to God) that poor Church was not totally deſtroy'd, yet ſhe was reduced to ſo lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing a Condition, that ſhe lay panting for Life and gaſping; and had ſhe not been powerfully and timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, muſt very ſoon have expired: And yet that Nation has granted his Majeſty (as in Duty and Gratitude they are bound) large Supplies, conſidering their mean Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, towards the payment of the Army, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining, or murmuring, among any Degree of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of the Country, from the higheſt to the loweſt; and will undoubtedly with all chearfulneſs imaginable, be always ready to do the like, according to their abilities, and the urgency of his Majeſty's Occaſions.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170932:24"/>
            <p>But to return from this Digreſſion, I muſt further ſay, That if all that call themſelves <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> were ſo intirely United as thoſe of <hi>Ireland, England</hi> would not be troubled with one kind of People; who, becauſe they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Favourites in the late Kings Reign, muſt needs be Enemies to the preſent; nor with another ſort, who are generally for any Government, but that which is actually in being. In ſhort, ſetting aſide that very ſmall number which I have already mentioned, a Man may converſe with the Proteſtants of that Kingdom, with as little danger of falling into the Company of that unaccountable People call'd <hi>Jacobites;</hi> as he is in, when he walks through the Fields and Meadows thereof, of treading upon Snakes or Adders, or any other poiſonous Vermin. For of all the Clergy of that Eſtabliſh'd Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> I have not heard of above three or four of any note that were thought worthy of any Preferment in the Church; who, either out of a principle of Conſcience, or in hopes of great Preferments, upon a Revolution, which I ſuppoſe may be now deſpair'd of, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to take the Oaths to his preſent Majeſty. Nor was there one Fellow of the Univerſity of <hi>Dublin</hi> that turn'd Tail in the late Revolution on any conſideration whatever, or refuſed the Oaths, when they were tendered to them: Nor indeed a private Graduat, or inferiour Scholar, except two or three <hi>Iriſh</hi> Lubbers, that plaid the Hypocrite ſome Years, for a little Bread and Learning; they indeed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in their proper Colours, but their Names are not worth the Dimenſions they would take up in Paper. And thus are both the Clergy of that Church, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations unalterably ſtanch, and firm to the Government of <hi>England</hi> both in Church and State, as it is by Law eſtabliſhed, to continue for ever in the hands of Proteſtant Princes.</p>
            <p>And yet theſe are the only People whom the afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Law (if it ſhould be enacted) is like ſeverely to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170932:25"/>affect; for, ſetting aſide thoſe Perſons of the firſt Quality, that are above any thing of Trade, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen of Eſtates, and the Farmers of the Lands of thoſe Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and others, have been all along, the only conſiderable Flock maſters of that Kingdom; ſome of them before the late War, were owners of 18000, others of 15000, ſome of 10000, ſome of 5000, and others of leſs numbers of Sheep according to their abilities, and the quantities of Land which they held. And I appeal to any one Man of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in <hi>England,</hi> that knew <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Year 1688, whether this be not a great Truth, and whether in the Provinces of <hi>Leinſter</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> and the other Parts of that Kingdom, where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations lay, were not all the conſiderable Sheep-walks in that Nation? And at this day the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there are owners of the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that kind of Cattle; for as ſoon as they were ſettled in their Eſtates and Farms, after the late War, they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to fall into the ſame Stock. And whether they do not, for the moſt part ſupply this Kingdom with thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of Wooll that come from thence, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants may ſoon inform themſelves by their Factors in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and I could name the moſt conſiderable of thoſe Sheep-maſters here or elſewhere, were there occaſion for it.</p>
            <p>As for the vulgar <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> they are the only Woollen Manufacturers, the Clothiers, Weavers, Dyers, Wooſted-Combers, Hatters, and of all other Trades which belong to this Manufacture, in and throughout the whole Kingdom. I am very well aſſured that there are within the City and Suburbs of <hi>Dublin,</hi> above 12000 <hi>Engliſh</hi> Families of this kind of Tradeſmen, of which there are computed to be above 50000 in that Nation who were bred to theſe Callings, and whoſe Genius leads them this particular way; and to diſable them from following thoſe Trades, and oblige them to earn their Bread by falling to work about Linnen Manufacture (as I have heard ſome Men propoſe ſince I
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170932:25"/>came to <hi>London,</hi> who in their own Opinion, were of no ſmall reach in Matters of Trade, nor in the Politicks nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) would be as hard and impracticable, as 'twould be to oblige all the <hi>Taylors</hi> in <hi>London</hi> to turn <hi>Shoemakers,</hi> or the <hi>Ribbon-Weavers</hi> to turn <hi>Clothiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There has indeed ſince the late War, an attempt been made, to ſet up a Linnen Manufacture in or near <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſome of the greateſt Men of the Kingdom were concern'd in it, who to encourage it, laid in conſiderable Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; but (as I heard from them that better underſtand the matter) it fell very ſhort of what the Undertakers propoſed by it in the beginning, for the Northern People ſupply that Country at cheaper Rates than the other could well afford it: Tho' 'tis very probable, that if the Parliament of <hi>Ireland</hi> give due Encouragement to ſuch as ſhall engage in the Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Manufactures (as we hear they intend to do) the growing ſet of young People, as well the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as others may betake themſelves thereto; and conſequently in ſome time, the Wollen Manufacturers Trade in that Kingdom, may in a great meaſure fall of it ſelf: but to impoſe it upon the preſent Generation, is altogether impracticable, and muſt prove ruinous to them.</p>
            <p>But theſe are Matters of Fact, and the Proof of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon Teſtimony, wherefore I ſhall only with all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Humility, propoſe to the Honourable the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or the Committee appointed by them, to enquire into Matters of this nature, who, I am ſure, will think it reaſonable to make a full Scrutiny into Affairs of that grand Importance, before they give their poſitive Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them to the Houſe; I ſay, I ſhall only humbly offer to them, that they will examine ſome of thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen who are unintereſted in that Kingdom, and have had occaſion to travel thither both before and ſince the late War (of which there are ſeveral in, and about <hi>London,</hi> and when occaſion ſhall offer, may be eaſily found) and let them
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170932:26"/>declare their Knowledge and their Sentiments in this matter, and I do not doubt, but they will be of the ſame Opinion with me, that if any one ſhould endeavour to perſwade the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to paſs ſuch a Law, he muſt be thought to level it againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Kingdom only, and that if he be a true Friend to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt of that Nation, or to the eſtabliſh'd Church, either here or there, he muſt needs be a very great Stranger to the Affairs and Conſtitution of that Country.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> muſt ſee things at that diſtance with other Men's Eyes, and may be abuſed, and impoſed upon, by malicious and falſe Suggeſtions, tho' they were the wiſeſt Aſſembly upon Earth, as indeed they have appear'd to be, by their wonderful Conduct during the late grand Revolution, and the Wars after it. But when they are better inform'd, 'tis to be hop'd they will think it their Buſineſs, rather to encourage, than ruin the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Nation, that is, if any inhabiting there may be thought <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men; for a Man may travel out of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> to <hi>Africk, Aſia,</hi> or <hi>America,</hi> remove his Family with him, if he think convenient, live as long as he pleaſes in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factories of thoſe Countries, and have Sons and Daughters born to him: and if he and they happen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into <hi>England,</hi> they ſhall not be denied either the Title or Priviledge of <hi>Engliſh</hi> People. But let a Man once land upon <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ground, breath of that Air, drink one Diſh of St. <hi>Patrick</hi>'s Well, and eſpecially if he live there ſome few Years; upon his return hither, he muſt reſt ſatisfied with the odious Character of an <hi>Iriſh-man.</hi> And yet there are no People under Heaven that have ſuffered ſo much for being <hi>Engliſh</hi> as they have done; no <hi>Amboyna,</hi> nor any other Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have been Maſters of, in the remoteſt and moſt barbarous Parts of the World, have ever ſeen ſuch Cruelties acted in them, as have been exerciſed by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts on the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which will abundantly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170932:26"/>appear to any one that will be at the trouble of reading the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of that Country, particularly Sir <hi>John Temple</hi>'s Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the grand Rebellion begun in the Year 1641.</p>
            <p>It muſt needs therefore be a very great Grief to all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Perſons among them, to think, that they ſhould be eſteemed as Strangers and Foreigners by their Friends in <hi>England;</hi> and becauſe they do but begin to look like what they formerly were, and to recover ſome part of thoſe great Loſſes which they ſuſtain'd in the late War, that they ſhould be look'd upon by <hi>England</hi> with a jealous Eye; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſuſpected to be rich (which God knows, and they know themſelves to their ſorrow, is a groundleſs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake) that an effectual courſe ſhould be taken at once to cruſh and ruin them: But to ſhew further, how great a trouble this muſt needs be to all thinking Men among them, let us conſider the Caſe of one particular Man, with whom I am very intimately acquainted. His Grandfather, being the firſt of the Family, that remov'd into that Kingdom, was barbarouſly murdered for no other reaſon, but for being an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant; ſeveral others of his neareſt Relations periſhed then upon the ſame account, and ſuch of them as eſcaped with their Lives, were ſtript and ruined, and in the late War both they and he were great Sufferers; he was himſelf during that War all along in the King's Service, his Father was proclaimed Rebel, for raiſing Men, and holding out a Garriſon againſt the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, and killing conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Numbers of them, and a conſiderable Sum of Money offered for his Head; one of this Man's Brother-in-Law was hang'd and quarter'd in the beginning of the Year 1689. for raiſing Men for his preſent Majeſty's Service, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kill'd in <hi>Flanders,</hi> his Brothers and other Relations were in the Armies of <hi>Enniskillin,</hi> and <hi>Londonderry;</hi> and moſt of them that are capable of bearing Arms, have been all along the Wars in <hi>Flanders</hi> in his Majeſty's Service, and that this Man muſt now be look'd upon as an <hi>Iriſh man</hi> and an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170932:27"/>debarr'd of the Priviledges of an <hi>Engliſh man,</hi> and thoſe Commodities with which it hath pleaſed God to bleſs his Country, rendered almoſt uſeleſs to him and his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: this Man muſt certainly think this a piece of great hardſhip and cruelty, and it muſt occaſion in him ſome very diſpiriting and melancholly Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Tho' this be literally true, yet I do not make it one Man's Caſe in particular; for there are very few of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility, Gentry, or Commonalty of that Kingdom, eſpecially if their Families have been of ſo long a ſtanding as the Year 1641. but can truly ſay that their Caſe is much like this, and that ſomething of the ſame kind has happened to them. So that if we ſhould ſuppoſe that it lay in the Power of <hi>England</hi> to ſink the whole Iſland of <hi>Ireland</hi> into the bottom of the Sea (which a great many do very poſitively, tho' very raſhly and groundleſly affirm, would be for the Intereſt of <hi>England)</hi> we might reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably expect, that they who receiv'd us ſo kindly and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately, when we were in real Diſtreſs (of which I have already ſaid ſomething) would either ſpare the Country for our ſake, or at leaſt imitate Heaven in the caſe of <hi>Lot</hi> and his Family, call us out of that hated place, before they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it, and provide for us a <hi>Zoar</hi> elſewhere. Or ſince they can only make it poor and miſerable, we might alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that they would in ſome meaſure conſult our Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Safety, have ſome kind of tenderneſs for us, and at leaſt, reſerve us for the laſt morſel. But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, tho' we be not the offending Party, never could be taxed for any diſobedience to <hi>England,</hi> upon which we have our whole Dependance in extremity or trouble, and are the principal Men they expect ſhould ſtand their Ground, and ſecure their Intereſt in that Country for them, yet we are the only People, who, if this Law be enacted, are ſingled out for Deſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170932:27"/>
            <p>Now to ſhew farther how great a ſeverity this would be, let us change the Scene, and ſuppoſe that a Law of this nature were intended againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Inhabitants of any one of our Foreign Plantations, as thoſe of <hi>Newfound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in particular, whoſe Caſe is not very unlike to ours; the <hi>French</hi> not long ago invaded thoſe Coaſts, landed a Party of Soldiers there, who committed all manner of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilities where-ever they came; took one or more of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications, and reduced the Inhabitants, who are Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> to a moſt wretched and lamentable Condition, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that ſome hundreds of them were forced to fly for Refuge into other Countries or Plantations. And to redreſs theſe Injuries, <hi>England</hi> thought convenient to fit out a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Ships, with ſome Regiments of Land-Forces, which were ſent upon that Expedition, not without a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Expence to the Nation. Now this Expedition being over, and thoſe poor People being ſettled in their former Habitations, begin to follow their reſpective Imployments, and retrieve ſome part of the great Loſſes which they ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Enemy; ſhould <hi>England</hi> now take up a prejudice againſt them, give them the denomination of <hi>Americans,</hi> or <hi>Indians,</hi> and impoſe ſuch ſevere Rules or Laws upon them, in reſpect to their Trade or Commerce; that ſuch of them as could live elſewhere, muſt quit that Country, and ſuch other poor People as could not ſo eaſily remove from thence, muſt be reduced to ſo miſerable and low a Condition, that they muſt lie obnoxious to the cruelties and fury of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Indians,</hi> or any other Enemy that ſhould think fit to attack them: this would, in all probability, bring <hi>England</hi> in ſome few Years, under the neceſſity either of quitting their Pretenſions to that Colony, or ſending another Fleet and Army to regain it, and would rather be thought Cruelty or Infatuation, than Prudence or good Management. And yet I know not how it comes to be thought otherwiſe in reference to <hi>Ireland,</hi> which is eſteemed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170932:28"/>by all the wiſe Men of <hi>England,</hi> as much more neceſſary and precious, than <hi>Newfoundland,</hi> or any other Plantation or Colony of that kind, as their Gold and Silver is, in compariſon to their Half-pence and Farthings. And if they rightly conſider the matter, they cannot but conclude, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> (let them call us <hi>Iriſh-men,</hi> or what they pleaſe) are a body of Men, which next to themſelves in <hi>Great Britain,</hi> they ought to love and value more than any People under Heaven; ſince we are Fleſh of their Fleſh, and Bone of their Bone, and there is ſo natural and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate a Relation and Connexion between them and us, that we are always ready to ſtand or fall, to be happy or miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable with them.</p>
            <p>It would be thought very unnatural and barbarous (were there any one ſo mad as to be guilty of ſuch a thing) that a Man ſhould be angry with his Hand or Foot, and ſhould therefore uſe means to prevent the Circulation of the Blood, and ſtop the Paſſage of the common Nutriment of the Body, into that part: this would, in all human probability, cauſe ſuch violent Diſtempers in the Body, as might occaſion the Stag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the whole Maſs of Blood, and the Diſſolution of the Body. And this is certainly, in a politick Senſe, the Caſe of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> If it be neceſſary for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and well being of this Nation, that the Soveraignty of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould ſtill be continued to the Kings of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and yet that the People of <hi>England</hi> will rather chooſe to ruin the intire Intereſts of their Friends in that Country, than ſuffer them to turn the moſt beneficial Productions thereof, to their Advantage; it may in ſome time prove very prejudicial, if not fatal to the People of <hi>England</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which will further appear from the more than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, if not the neceſſary Conſequences of ſuch a Statute; which I ſhall endeavour as briefly and plainly as I can, to offer to the Conſideration of ſuch as will vouchſafe to peruſe this Paper. And</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170932:28"/>1. The firſt and immediate Conſequence that muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow the promulgation of ſuch a Law, will be the unavoidable Ruin of thoſe many Thouſands of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, who live by the Woollen Manufactures in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in which the Strength of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in that Kingdom, doth in a great meaſure conſiſt; when their Trades are rendred uſeleſs to them, and they are incapacitated of earning their Bread thereby; they muſt (at leaſt the greater part of them) remove themſelves and their Families into ſome other part of the World, where they may hope for a livelihood, for in <hi>Ireland</hi> 'twill be morally impoſſible they ſhould have it, ſince Tradeſmen of this kind are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Strangers to all Callings, except thoſe in which they were educated. To <hi>England</hi> great part of them dare no more venture, than thoſe who ſince laſt Seſſion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tranſplanted themſelves from the <hi>Fryars</hi> and other priviledged Places; and tho' 'tis not to be believed that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> would deliberately and wilfully do any thing that may leſſen the number of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and weaken their own Intereſt in <hi>Ireland;</hi> yet if we ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that they ſhould enact ſuch Laws for the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Tradeſmen, by which their Creditors in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> muſt be very eaſy to them, or indeed forgive them their whole Debts, even this would not prove a ſufficient motive to them for returning into <hi>England;</hi> for if they could not live here in the beginning of their time, much leſs will they be now able to ſubſiſt by what they ſhall earn, having been accuſtomed to the exuberant Plenty and Cheapneſs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and having generally very numerous Families, that Country being remarkably fruitful for the procreation of Children.</p>
            <p>If they ſhould remove to <hi>Scotland,</hi> as 'tis not unlikely many of them would upon ſuch an occaſion, that Country being much cheaper than <hi>England,</hi> and it being not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that there would be great Encouragements propoſed to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170932:29"/>them there; they muſt in all probability imbody with the <hi>Scotch,</hi> and become one People with them, in relation both to their Religion, and Civil Intereſts; for we know by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Experience, that Men of thoſe ordinary Capacities are but too prone, and eaſy to be drawn away from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient eſtabliſhed Church of theſe Nations, eſpecially when they can propoſe to themſelves any temporal Advantages thereby; and by this means, the People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with their Correſpondents and Friends in <hi>Ireland</hi> (both their Intereſts being inſeparable) will not only be the eaſier and cheaper furniſhed with Woollen Manufactures to carry on their <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, but will be capacitated to Trade to the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> alſo, and that notwithſtanding the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction laid, or to be laid upon them by <hi>England,</hi> that they ſhould not carry any Commodities to the Weſtern Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, except Servants and Proviſions, which is all the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> are allowed to tranſport into that part of the World: they will (I ſay) by this means be in a great meaſure enabled to carry on a Trade to <hi>America,</hi> that is, if what they have lately ſaid in the Caſe of the <hi>Royal-Fiſhery</hi> be allowed them; that being a free, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered People, no Laws can affect them, but ſuch as are of their own making, and that conſequently they have a right to Trade abroad wherever the <hi>Engliſh</hi> do; that there has been lately a Diſpute of this kind between the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men concern'd in the <hi>Royal-Fiſhery,</hi> and the People of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> concerning Freedom and Priviledge, I am very well ſatisfied the former can and will teſtify.</p>
            <p>But I will allow that this may be a Miſtake in me, and that the <hi>Scotch</hi> muſt in this particular be over ruled by <hi>England:</hi> yet as for their <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, that is undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; the Conſequence of which will be, that ſince there are ſo great Immunities allowed them in reference to that Trade, and Piracy is at an end, they will proſecute it with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and vigour, and will, by the Aſſiſtance of their Friends
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170932:29"/>and Correſpondents in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who will undoubtedly be concern'd with them, be enabled to make a conſiderable progreſs therein, and will furniſh <hi>Ireland</hi> with all manner of <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Goods, at much cheaper Rates than the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants can afford them; So that thoſe conſiderable Sums of Money which come yearly out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for Silks, Muſlins, Bengals, Cotton, Rice, and all other Commodities which come from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> (where the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> have no manner of Traffick) will be totally loſt to <hi>England,</hi> and a great means of enriching <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order to which end, they will not want the Wool of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that is, if any of the Flock-maſters of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhall think it worth their while to deal in Sheep, as it cannot well be ſuppoſed they will, if this Law be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted; and that, in ſpight of all the Laws that can, or ſhall be made by <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to prevent them, and all the diligence which ſhall be uſed to have thoſe Laws duly executed, the <hi>Scotch</hi> (I ſay) notwithſtanding all theſe means will have the Wool of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or great part of it, tranſported into <hi>Scotland,</hi> except we could ſuppoſe that there might be Officers day and night on the Watch, in all the Creeks and Corners of the Sea Coaſts of the North of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> for it being but about three Hours ſail from thence to <hi>Scotland,</hi> they may, in the dead of night, load their open Boats (in which 'tis common with them to go to Market to <hi>Ireland)</hi> with what Goods they and their Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents ſhall think convenient, and be at their Port in their own Country, before the next morning, or at leaſt out of the reach of thoſe concern'd in the Revenue of <hi>Ireland:</hi> and undoubtedly this has been often practiſed for ſome Years paſt, to the great prejudice of <hi>England,</hi> and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of <hi>France;</hi> and we may be ſure it will be more indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly continued now than ever, eſpeciaily if they can find the way of having it wrought up in their own Country,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170932:30"/>and ſending it abroad to Foreign Markets; for ſince there are thoſe People called <hi>Owlers</hi> even in <hi>England,</hi> and under the Eye of the Government, notwithſtanding the ſtrict and Penal Laws that are againſt them, and the great Care and Diligence that are uſed to prevent them, we may very well expect the like Dealings between <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> who have much greater Opportunities of carrying on a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of that kind, than 'tis poſſible for <hi>England</hi> to have with <hi>France,</hi> or any other Country.</p>
            <p>But let us ſuppoſe that thoſe ruined Manufacturers ſhould Tranſport themſelves and their Families into <hi>Holland,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Foreign Countries, and they, and their Poſterity be for ever loſt to theſe Kingdoms; the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Popiſh Merchants will have then, by reaſon of the Cheapneſs of Wool, greater Encouragement for carrying on their old Woollen Trade with <hi>France</hi> than ever; for tho' by Act of Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> 'tis made Felony, without <hi>Benefit of Clergy,</hi> to Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport Wool into any Foreign part of the World, except <hi>England,</hi> or even to put any on Ship board clandeſtinely, yet I have ſeen ſeveral that were taken in the Fact, tried for their Lives, but matters were ſo ordered by the Intereſt of the Merchants of thoſe Towns, where the Offences were committed, that I never knew any of the Offenders ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Another way they have for Tranſporting Wool into <hi>France</hi> (to make out the Deficiencies of the former) by which many of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Merchants have frequently tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported whole Ship-loads, to that degree, that they are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foully belied, or have purchaſed conſiderable Eſtates with the vaſt ſumms of Money which they have gained by that illegal Commerce: for there is a Clauſe in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Act, which requires that all Perſons whatſoever who ſhall Tranſport Wool from <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> ſhall before they put it on Ship-board, enter it into the Cuſtom-Houſe of the reſpective Port where it is Shipped, and ſhall bring ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170932:30"/>Security to the Collector of the ſaid Cuſtom houſe, and enter into Bonds, that the Wool ſo Shipped ſhould be landed and diſpoſed of, in ſome Port of <hi>England,</hi> and that the Merchants ſhould in a certain limited time, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Certificates to that purpoſe from <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Stratagem which they uſed to evade this, is as follows; Firſt they entered the Ship in, and ſometimes by a wrong Name; and in the next place, they either brought ſome Bankrupt Fellows, who pretended to be Men of Credit and Reputation in the World, to perfect thoſe Bonds which the Law required, and who could upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion eaſily abſcond and fruſtrate the Deſign of the Law in that caſe; or otherwiſe, they brought Perſons, who by their Habit and Behaviour ſeem'd, and perhaps were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Men, but gave themſelves Names of Perſons dead long before, or perhaps of ſuch, as they never knew to have been in the World: And having thus deceived the Officers of the Cuſtom-Houſe, they convey'd vaſt quantities of Wool into <hi>France:</hi> And if at any time the Merchant fear'd or heard, that his Ship was diſcovered to have put this Trick on thoſe concern'd in the Revenue, he immediately gave orders ſhe ſhould be ſold, and another bought in <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Holland.</hi> That this has been often practiſed, will appear by the VVool-Bonds taken in <hi>Ireland</hi> for ſeveral Years before the late VVar, for ſome thouſands of pounds, ſubſcribed with Names as fictitious as thoſe of <hi>John a Nokes</hi> or <hi>John-a Styles.</hi> And I do really think, that there is now one worthy Member in the Houſe of Commons of <hi>England,</hi> who can affirm this to be true, for he was (if I miſtake not) the firſt diſcoverer of thoſe Practices, having been concern'd in the Revenues of <hi>Ireland</hi> for ſome Years, and may perhaps be beſt able to give directions how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that Trade for the future, that is, as far as 'tis poſſible it ſhould be hindred.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170932:31"/>
            <p>For it is but reaſonable to conclude, that if VVool be reduced to a lower value than it was at in thoſe times, as it neceſſarily muſt, if that Law be enacted; that then thoſe Merchants and their Confederates will run all hazards in carrying on the ſame beneficial Trade for the future, and 'twill be next to an impoſſibility to prevent them; there being Bays and Harbours capable of receiving Ships in the moſt deſart and mountainous Maritim parts of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; from whence it will not lie in the power of Man to hinder their conveying of what Commodities they ſhall think convenient, to any Country where they may expect a kind Reception.</p>
            <p>But it may perhaps be here objected, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Kingdom are concern'd in this Owling Trade as well as others.</p>
            <p>To which I muſt anſwer, That if there be ſome few particular Perſons, that have either married the Daughters, or learn'd the Manners of the People of the Land, who have been thus guilty, 'tis not my buſineſs to juſtifie them. But the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in general, are Men of greater Loyalty, Conſcience, and Honeſty, than for private gain to do any thing that may be a wrong to their King, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the publick good of their Country; the truth of which will abundantly appear to any one that conſiders the ſtrict and ſevere Laws they have made in relation to this particular. And indeed there are but very few <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dealers in the Sea-Ports of that Kingdom, where theſe Cheats are generally practiſed; for beſides the under-hand Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances that have been frequently made uſe of to ruin any <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> that ſets up a Trade there, the adjacent parts of the Country are moſtly inhabited by People that will not deal with any <hi>Engliſh man,</hi> for any thing they can be furniſh'd with by thoſe of their own Country or Profeſſion; and if the <hi>Iriſh</hi> be ſuffered again to go on with this VVool-Trade (of which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Country's being prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170932:31"/>to go on with their Manufactures, would in a great meaſure hinder them) it will be a great means of enabling them to come in for a ſnack of the Eſtates of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there. For</p>
            <p>Secondly. Another Conſequence of that Law (if en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted) will be the Ruin of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen and Farmers, who (as I have already ſaid) are the principal, if not the only conſiderable Flock-maſters of that Kingdom. For if the Manufactures be diſcouraged and run down; and the Manufacturers forced to leave the Country, the prices of Wool muſt fall of courſe, and conſequently the value of Sheep alſo. The Farmers (whoſe principal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance has always conſiſted in that kind of Cattel) will not be able to pay their Rents, and in their own defence muſt throw up their Leaſes to their Landlords, who by this means muſt needs be fellow-ſufferers with them, and will neither be well able, nor indeed willing to hold their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates in that Kingdom, which will not ſeem a Paradox, if we conſider,</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Country are the only ſufferers by the late War: many of them, that had Eſtates, or a Title to Eſtates, which was the moſt they had in thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Times, raiſed conſiderable Sums of Money among their Friends in <hi>England,</hi> to equip them for the Army; or put them in a condition of returning into their own Country. Others, who owed Debts before, were by the loſs of their Eſtates, both real and perſonal, and the great Intereſt of Money in that Kingdom, rendered uncapable of paying off thoſe Debts; which are the true Cauſes, that ſo many of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Eſtates there are, this day, ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encumber'd. 'Tis not good Manners to name Noblemen, and Gentlemen, upon this occaſion: but this is certainly the Condition of many of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Landlords in <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the higheſt Rank to the loweſt: and the great means which many of them propoſed for the recovery of their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170932:32"/>loſſes, and their future ſecurity, were the raiſing of Flocks, and the encouragement of the Woollen Manufactures; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards which ends, not a few of them, have laid out great part of what Money they could procure after the War, in Sheep; and have given great encouragements to Tradeſmen of all kinds, who are fit for that purpoſe; by letting them convenient Lands at eaſie Rates, and building them Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, ſome at their own private expence; and others at the publick charge, even in the remoteſt, and moſt <hi>Iriſh</hi> Counties of that Kingdom; with an intent to plant <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colonies, that may be able to ſecure themſelves, and ſnub the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whenever they ſhall perceive them begin to grow high and inſolent: And if this Law paſs, that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, as well as Uſeful Deſign, muſt neceſſarily fall to the ground; and end in the inevitable ruin of thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> Manufacturers and Farmers; and the great detriment of the Landlords; the laſt of which will, many of them, be forced to Sell or Mortgage their Eſtates to ſatisfie their Creditors.</p>
            <p>Or let us ſuppoſe (as 'tis but reaſonable we ſhould) that many of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen of <hi>Ireland</hi> have been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Husbands than others, and have not only good Eſtates in Lands, but have Money by them; ſo that the loſs of their Flocks cannot be of ſuch very ill conſequence to them; but that they may live plentifully without them, either by Tenanting their Lands with the vulgar <hi>Iriſh,</hi> or by dealing in other Stock, ſuch as Black Cattel, Horſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And let us ſuppoſe that thoſe other Gentlemen, whoſe Fortunes are encumbered, ſhould by being good Husbands, or living poorly, have a proſpect of getting over thoſe difficulties, and clearing their Eſtates in ſome Years: Yet if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt be run down, and their Numbers ſo leſſened, as by this Law they muſt needs be, neither the one nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will think it ſafe to continue in a Country, where they have themſelves ſo lately, and their Anceſtors ſo often heretofore been ſufferers: but will rather chooſe to diſpoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170932:32"/>of their Eſtates there, and purchaſe ſome ſmall Concerns, where they may live with ſome ſecurity, and partake of the Privileges of <hi>Engliſh men</hi> or Free Subjects, from which a Law of this kind muſt undeniably exclude them.</p>
            <p>Now the Purchaſers of thoſe Lands, muſt be either the <hi>Iriſh</hi> or the <hi>Scotch;</hi> or moſt probably they will both be Sharers; if the <hi>Iriſh</hi> get a conſiderable part of them, they will in a few Years be in a condition of affording large aſſiſtance to any Foreign Prince, or pretended Popiſh-Heir, that may endeavour to diſturb the Peace and Tranquility of theſe Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>But 'tis likely the <hi>Scotch</hi> will be the greater Purchaſers, and by that means grow Rich and Formidable, and able to ſtand by <hi>England</hi> with their Lives and Fortunes, againſt all that ſhall oppoſe them: And to be the ſame eaſie and neighbourly People, that they have been from the time of the ancient <hi>Picts</hi> (when Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> tells us, their Friends in <hi>Scotland</hi> began to make frequent Viſits into <hi>England</hi>) down to our own Times. But leſt I ſhould ſeem to deſign this as an Invective, and to incenſe <hi>England</hi> againſt them; and withal to be as Impertinent, as we ſhould ſuppoſe a Stranger to have been, that ſhould have come into the City of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> in her proſperity, and told that People a Story out of their own Chronicles, how vexatious the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in their neighbouring Countries had been to them for many Ages. I ſhall therefore only ſay further, that both the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and they have, ſo lately that we cannot yet forget it, given us evident Demonſtrations, how they would deal with us, if we lay at their Mercy; and this they did at the ſame time, with this only difference, that the latter did their Work more effectually than the others; the <hi>Iriſh</hi> did theirs in the time of VVar and Tyranny, and were themſelves, and their pretended Act of Parliament, ſoon kick'd out of doors. But the <hi>Scotch,</hi> taking the advantge of a time when <hi>England</hi> was not at leiſure to take notice of their Proceedings, ruin'd
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170932:33"/>the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by a Law, which is like to prove but too firm and laſting; which leads me</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To a third Conſequence, and one that I think, doth neceſſarily and evidently follow from what has been now ſaid; and that is, that if the High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould paſs ſuch a Law as afore-mentioned, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> or <hi>Scotch</hi> become Maſters of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Church which is now eſtabliſhed there, muſt inevitably be ruined: which indeed is the main Conſideration that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged me in this Undertaking.</p>
            <p>I heard the Queſtion propoſed ſince I came to <hi>London, What the Church had to do with Trade? or how a Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Woollen Manufacture could affect it?</hi> as if the whole Body of the People were not of the Church, nor the Clergy Members of the Commonwealth; but their Intereſts were different, and did not ſtand upon the ſame Baſis with the eſtabliſh'd <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws of that Kingdom. And I think it might as well have been ask'd, What it concern'd the Church of <hi>England,</hi> if the grand Fleet had been burnt by the <hi>French</hi> in the late War? or the Church of <hi>Spain,</hi> if the Galleons had been taken by Monſieur <hi>Ponty?</hi> But becauſe it may not be thought a good way to anſwer one Queſtion, by propoſing others, I ſhall in few words give a direct anſwer to it: I have already ſhewn how far this Statute muſt affect the Laity of the eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>Ireland:</hi> and ſhall now endeavour to ſhew how far the Eccleſiaſticks or the Church, ſtrictly ſo called, muſt be concern'd in this matter. Tho', methinks, 'tis needleſs to tell the World, that if the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty, of that, or any other Nation be reduced to a low Ebb of Fortune, the Clergy muſt, by neceſſary conſequence, bear a part in the common Sufferings, except that part of the World where the Church hath engroſſed all to herſelf, and made the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try poor and miſerable; and it is not long ſince we have by fatal Experience, found this to be true in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170932:33"/>
            <p>But for greater Evidence ſake, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew the Methods, by which that Church was ruined, to that Degree, that the Clergy who lived in thoſe Parts of the Country, where the <hi>Iriſh</hi> principally inhabited, had for two Years before the War, little more than the Name of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings; for they muſt either have ſet their Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> at what Rates they thought fit to offer, or they would pay little or none in kind; for the moſt expeditious means which the Clergy of that Kingdom had (or indeed have now) for the recovery of their dues, is a Statute paſſed in <hi>England,</hi> in the Twenty Seventh of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. which men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>Ireland</hi> as well as <hi>England,</hi> and ordains, that if any Perſon being cited in a Decimary Cauſe to the Eccleſiaſtical Court, refuſed to appear, that then two Juſtices of the Peace (whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) ſhall upon the Receipt of a Certificate under the Seal of that Court, ſignifying his Contumacy, iſſue their Warrant againſt the Party ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending; and if he refuſe to enter ſufficient Security, that he will appear at a prefix'd time, and pay what by the ſaid Court ſhall be adjudged againſt him, that then he ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſafe Cuſtody, till he make Satisfaction; which Law was commonly put in execution in ſeveral Dioceſſes of that Kingdom, and met with no oppoſition while Proteſtant Judges ſat on the Bench; but they were no ſooner thruſt out, and Popiſh Judges appointed, but that Practice was declared ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, and that Statute to be of no force in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſeveral Juſtices of the Peace diſcarded, for having iſſued their War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants purſuant thereto.</p>
            <p>By another Statute, which was made in <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Three and Thirtieth Year of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. it is enacted, That if the Party ſummoned for Detention or Subſtraction of Tythes, ſhall enter his appearance in the Eccleſiaſtical Court, and Sentence ſhall paſs there againſt him, that then two Juſtices of the Peace, qualified as aforeſaid, ſhall at the requeſt of the ſaid Court, impriſon the ſaid Offender,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170932:34"/>without Bail or Main-prize, till he fulfil the Sentence ſo pronounced againſt him. But the intent of this Law was in thoſe days eaſily deſeated, for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> throughout the Kingdom were adviſed by their Lawyers to take no notice of any Citations iſſued out of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</p>
            <p>So that the only Method which then remained of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt Offenders of that kind, was to proſecute them to Excommunication, and to take Writs <hi>de Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat, capient.</hi> out of the High Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> which by reaſon of the great Charge of thoſe Writs, is not to be done, but upon extraordinary occaſions, and where the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conteſted is conſiderable: however, to prevent even this Practice, as well as to obſtruct the common Courſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in all Caſes, where a Proteſtant was concern'd againſt a Papiſt, the Lord Chancellor Sir <hi>Charles Porter,</hi> who was a true Friend to the eſtabliſh'd Church, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, was diſplaced to make room for a profeſs'd, malicious Papiſt, who utterly refuſed the Clergy the Benefit of the Law in caſes of that kind, and left the Laity of what Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſoever, to pay their Miniſters what they thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient; ſo that 'tis plain, that if either the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> or <hi>Scotch</hi> have that one Miniſter of Juſtice on their ſide, that ſhall be no Friend to the eſtabliſh'd Church, but ſhall diſcountenance the Proceedings of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, he may him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſingly go a great way towards the ruin of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Epiſcopal Clergy of that Nation.</p>
            <p>And indeed it happened very well for them, that thoſe Writs were not granted them by that Popiſh Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor: for he, by the Direction of the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> had made <hi>Iriſh</hi> High Sheriffs in moſt of the Counties of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who would execute neither Writ, nor Decree on any Papiſt, either for Clergy-man, or Lay-man.</p>
            <p>I think likewiſe that I have laid down ſufficient Reaſons to make us believe, that if the <hi>Scotch</hi> Presbyterians had the Eſtates of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and conſequently the Magiſtracy and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170932:34"/>Power in their Hands, they would ſerve the Epiſcopal Clergy, and ſuch as ſhould adhere to them, after the ſame manner. The Queſtion therefore that remains, is whether it be not probable that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and they (whoſe Intereſts ſeem now to be ſo oppoſite to each other) might upon occaſion of ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Epiſcopal Proteſtant Church, ſhould they find a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Opportunity for that purpoſe, be reconciled, and joyn in that great Work, as the Evangeliſt tells us, <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> were upon the Tryal and Condemnation of our Saviour, notwithſtanding the Animoſities that were between them before, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.12.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. Let us ſuppoſe that ſuch a Conjunction may never happen between the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch,</hi> but that the <hi>Scotch</hi> alone may be Maſters of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, they muſt in ſome proceſs of time; that is, if the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> of that Kingdom be diſcouraged by <hi>England;</hi> that both <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> be of a piece, and that 'tis not impoſſible they may have ſome Friends and Adherents in this Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> this being ſuppoſed, I do not doubt but all conſiderate Men, if they will declare their Sentiments ingenuouſly, will own, that it may very ſeverely affect the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and eſpecially the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by Law eſtabliſh'd; for that ſacred Vine had but two main Plants that ſprang from her, the one, which was that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> is cut up by the Roots already; and the ſame ſacrilegious Hands, or ſome of the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>amp are at work on the other, which is that of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and theſe two being cleared out of the way, they may the more readily come at the Main-Body. Tho' this may ſeem to be a very remote <hi>Conſequence</hi> from the aforeſaid Law, if enacted, yet it is not unworthy the thoughts of all ſuch as are well-wiſhers to the Church, and the publick welfare of <hi>England,</hi> to whom I ſhall leave, and earneſtly recommend the further Conſideration thereof.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170932:35"/>
            <p>I do not ſuggeſt theſe things through a fear that any evil of this kind may happen to us during the Reign of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Glorious Majeſty King <hi>William;</hi> for if common Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Honeſty, Intereſt, and the Conſideration of thoſe many excellent things, which he has done for theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and <hi>Europe</hi> in general, be not ſufficient Motives to keep all manner of Proteſtants within his Dominions, firm and loyal to him, yet his Wiſdom, Power and Conduct cannot eaſily fail of that end. But we muſt not expect to enjoy always a Prince of his vaſt Experience in the World, the wiſeſt of Councellors, and the beſt, and braveſt of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals; a Prince of ſo much Honour, Virtue and Goodneſs, ſo highly valued and eſteemed by moſt of all the Princes of <hi>Europe;</hi> ſo formidable to his Enemies, when he had any that were conſiderable; ſo entirely beloved by the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his Subjects; and who has juſtly merited more Praiſes, were it poſſible to ennumerate them, than the learned and ingenious <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his immortal Panegyrick, aſcribes to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour, for he it is, that by his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Wiſdom, and the repeated hazards of his Royal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, has ſecured to us our Eſtates, our Lives, our Liberties, our Religion; that has preſerved, or rather made the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Nation the greateſt People in this part of the World, and ſettled theſe Kingdoms upon ſuch firm Foundations for future Peace and Happineſs, as no Man living remembers us to have ſtood on before, and which cannot well be ſhaken but by diſagreement and confuſion among our ſelves. But my poor Encomiums are but as the Vapours which aſcend from Earth toward Heaven, and my mean Pen would but ſully his Glory; for which reaſon I ſhall leave the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth his Praiſes to the Maſters of Senſe and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and return to the matter in hand, by ſaying, that we muſt not expect to be always happy in a Prince of his wonderful Qualifications: for tho' his Heroic Spirit and Actions, by the Divine Aſſiſtance, have plac'd him in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170932:35"/>the higheſt Rank of thoſe which are called <hi>Gods upon Earth, yet he muſt die like a Man and fall like one of the Princes.</hi> And tho' (thanks be to God) the Wiſdom of this Nation hath ſettled the Succeſſion of the Crown, according to the Hearts deſire of all well-wiſhers to the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and future Monarchy, and we have a fair proſpect of Peace and Happineſs under thoſe who are appointed by Law to Reign over us; yet they are alſo ſubject to Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and many unexpected Events, may happen to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the preſent Circumſtances of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who are not the moſt united People in the World among themſelves, and muſt expect, not to want <hi>Popiſh Pretenders,</hi> who when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they can procure a Power, will think they have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Right to contend for the Crown.</p>
            <p>Now it is not reaſonable to believe that the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> when they have conſidered this matter, and are rightly inform'd concerning it, will, to gratify the Deſigns of any particular Perſons, enact a Law that may be fatal to Poſterity; and which perhaps may produce ſome evil Effects even in this preſent Generation, before a great many that are now alive may be ſummoned to another World: it being the ſure means to ruin a great many Thouſands of true Friends to the eſtabliſh'd Church of <hi>England,</hi> and in a great meaſure to ſtrengthen the Hands of her Enemies. For it is certain that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Kingdom are not only moſt unanimous and hearty in the Intereſts of the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both in Church and State; but are a People who have been bred to Arms, and have been moſt of them in actual Service in the late Wars, and are all ready to appear in a very conſiderable Body, whenever his Majeſty or his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Succeſſors ſhall have occaſion to command them; and will, according to their Abilities, give him, or ſuch his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors all other reaſonable Aſſiſtances, without the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining or murmuring.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170932:36"/>
            <p>For which Reaſons, it will not be unworthy the Grand Council of <hi>England</hi> to conſider further, that the ruin of that People by ſuch a Law, which ſeems to thwart the Methods of Divine Providence, in rendring the Bleſſings which Heaven hath beſtowed upon them, in a great meaſure, uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to them, muſt not only be look'd upon, as a very indifferent piece of Policy, but may be eſteemed by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God as a very great Sin, which tho' it may ſpring from the root of Covetouſneſs in ſome particular Perſons; yet if a Law be enacted to that purpoſe, it muſt then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come national, and may cauſe him, who alone can make a Kingdom rich and great, and happy, to ſtop the courſe of his Bleſſings, and divert thoſe overflowings of Proſperity, which <hi>England</hi> may in all human probability, expect by a firm and laſting Peace: For the making of a Law of this nature, will not only be the ſure means to prevent them from being rich, who are groundleſly ſuſpected of being ſo, and the ſending of them empty away: but will be alſo the taking of the Bread out of Thouſands of hungry Mouths, and will in effect, prove the ruin of a Church and People, that have very often ſuffered for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; and I may ſay, with a great deal of Truth, have upon many occaſions been eminently ſerviceable to them, but never offered them the leaſt provocation. And whether this may be confiſtent with the Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> I ſhall not preſume to determine, but ſince the moſt Learned Caſuiſts of the World, have a ſhare in the Legiſlative Power, I ſhall humbly ſubmit the matter to their Reſolution.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only propoſe one thing more to the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wiſe Men of <hi>England, viz.</hi> that if they would but agree to make the beſt of their own Manufactures, they would be ſo far from obſtructing the People of <hi>Ireland</hi>'s purſuing theirs; that 'tis very probable they would in a little time be for giving them Encouragements for going on vigorouſly with them: And the true method of raiſing the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170932:36"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> Manufactures to that pitch of perfection will be found to be extreamly eaſy and practicable, <hi>viz.</hi> let the great Men of the Nation unanimouſly reſolve, that both them ſelves and their Families will in their Apparel, be conten with the Fabricks, the Cloaths and Stuffs of their own Country, and that they will diſcountenance others that ſhall preſume the contrary; this will undoubtedly influence all ſuch as are in inferiour Stations through theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and his Majeſty's Foreign Plantations: and ingenious Artiſts will be hereby incouraged to improve the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Manufactures, tho' I am very well aſſured that there are thoſe in <hi>London</hi> already, that will undertake to furniſh the Nobility and Gentry of theſe Kingdoms with Silks, Stuffs, Cloaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſhall be as rich, beautiful and ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as any Nation under Heaven need to wiſh them, and at much cheaper Rates than 'tis poſſible to have them from abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juvenal</hi> deals very freely with the Antient <hi>Romans,</hi> and ſeems to be paſſionately concern'd, that they (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greateſt People upon Earth) did ape the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> in all particulars in their Habit, in their way of Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Drinking, Diſcourſe and Behaviour, and did (as he tells us) do moſt other things after the <hi>Greek</hi> Faſhion, and indeed theſe Nations have been faulty to that degree in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, with reſpect to the <hi>French,</hi> that I have heard ſome intelligent Perſons affirm, that in the two laſt Reigns, when an Embaſſador, ſuppoſe from <hi>Germany, Denmark,</hi> or <hi>Sweden</hi> had a deſire to make an agreeable Figure in the Court of <hi>England,</hi> he thought it could not be done, unleſs he had his Cloaths from <hi>France,</hi> from whence moſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility, and they that eſteem'd themſelves to be the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionable part of the Gentry had theirs; nor is Apparel the only thing in which they have been vainly fond of imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the <hi>French,</hi> for moſt of thoſe who reckon themſelves the only genteel People, when they come to an honeſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170932:37"/>Gentleman's Table, and find it furniſhed with good Beef, Mutton, Veal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they cannot away with <hi>that naſty Butchers Meat:</hi> Nor is the Poultry or Fowl thought fit for Stomachs of Quality, except they be ſo Frenchified, as to looſe their natural Taſte and Colour; but if they come to another place, and meet with a Diſh of Scraps, which perhaps were detain'd a Day or two before from the Poor, and that be toſs'd up after the <hi>French</hi> mode, O then 'tis excellent ſavory Victuals! little Maſter and Miſs are not thought to call decently for Bread or Small beer at Table, unleſs they can do it in <hi>French;</hi> nor is the Curtezan of the Town ſufficiently qualified to wheedle her eaſy <hi>Beau,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhe be in ſome meaſure Miſtreſs of the <hi>French</hi> Tongue; without which indeed, no one can be ſufficiently imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, nor bear a part in the noiſy Converſation which is now in faſhion. All this is certainly a kind of Homage paid to <hi>France,</hi> 'tis a <hi>tacit</hi> acknowledgement of ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies in them, of which we are not Maſters; and the owning ourſelves obliged to them for the melioration and true uſe of our Cloaths, Meat, Converſation and other Accommodations and Bleſſings of this Life.</p>
            <p>Tho' it may not be thought eaſy to reform in all theſe particulars at one time, yet methinks 'tis but reaſonable it ſhould be attempted in relation to our Cloaths, ſince that would be vaſtly advantageous to <hi>England,</hi> in keeping thoſe great Sums of Money at home, which before the War were ſent yearly to <hi>France</hi> for Silks, Stuffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'twould alſo be a means of employing many Thouſands of Hands, which by means of the great Importation of Foreign Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of that kind, do want Work; and 'tis very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that inſtead of prohibiting the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> from ſending their Manufactures out of their own Country, their Aſſiſtance would be required in furniſhing the Weſtern Plantations with thoſe coarſe Woollen Commodities, which they are now by Law, debarred of ſending to any of them.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170932:37"/>
            <p>For ſince our King has been the Glorious Inſtrument of retrieving <hi>the antient Grandeur and Honour of.</hi> England, and giving Peace to <hi>Europe,</hi> the Chriſtian Princes will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly pay him the Reſpects which are juſtly due to his Merits: Foreign Nations will be fond of imitating the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gallantry, and think <hi>London</hi> as competent a City for the Education of their young Nobility and Gentry in Arts and Arms, in Behaviour and Manners, as <hi>Paris</hi> has been this laſt Age eſteem'd by us: and conſequently, tho' perhaps <hi>France</hi> may think it below them to imitate our Faſhions, or buy our Silks, Stuffs, or Cloaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from us; yet we ſhall at leaſt be their Competitors, and other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>Europe</hi> will follow the Modes and buy the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of <hi>England:</hi> but if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation will think nothing becoming but what they have from <hi>France,</hi> 'tis no wonder the reſt of the World ſhould neglect thoſe things which are deſpiſed by ourſelves.</p>
            <p>This (I think) is a Conſideration much more worthy the Thoughts of the great Men of <hi>England,</hi> than that they ſhould ſtoop at a Game ſo mean as the poor incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Manufactures of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which, according to the beſt Information I can have in this Kingdom, do not amount to the two hundredth part of thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> and which, beſides their being already prohibited from being tranſported to the Weſtern Plantations, are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, that they will not ſell in any Foreign Markets, where <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commodities can be had, and yet they are the main Support of a People who (I may ſafely ſay) are as Faithful and Loyal to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> while fix'd on a Proteſtant Head, as Men can be, and whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts (I hope) the Wiſdom of <hi>England</hi> will not think fit to ſacrifice to the Covetouſneſs of particular Perſons, notwithſtanding the Petition of the Citizens of <hi>Exon,</hi> &amp;c. by which if they propoſe to have conſiderable Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170932:38"/>of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wool imported to them, they have taken the moſt effectual courſe to prevent the increaſe of Sheep, and the plenty of Wool in that Kingdom, for if a Law ſhould be enacted againſt the Exportation of Woollen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures from <hi>Ireland</hi> to any Foreign Parts, no Man of common Senſe will think it worth his while to deal in Sheep, which are the moſt nice and dangerous, and will by that means be the moſt unprofitable Cattel in which a Man can deal in that Country.</p>
            <p>For notwithſtanding the People of <hi>Exon</hi>'s Complaint of the want of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wool, I can produce undeniable Proof, that the very laſt Summer the Wool of the Weſtern part of that Kingdom lay on the Owners Hands for a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able time, the Factors concern'd for the <hi>Engliſh, Dublin</hi> and <hi>Cork</hi> Merchants having offered but five Shillings a Stone for the beſt Wool of a full Years growth, which is ſixteen Pound <hi>Averdupoize</hi> Weight, and 'tis certain that in <hi>Dublin</hi> the current Price of it was but ſeven Shillings and ſix Pence, and I am ready to demonſtrate that good three Year old Weathers in as full Wool as they could be at that time of the Year, were ſold in <hi>November</hi> laſt at five Pound a Score in the ſame part of <hi>Ireland.</hi> So that all the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> that are now in <hi>England,</hi> with whom I have had the Opportunity of Diſcourſing upon this Subject, are of Opinion that it had been a greater piece of Prudence in the Inhabitants of <hi>Exon,</hi> &amp;c. to have petitioned the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> that the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> might be encouraged to propagate that kind of Cattel, and not hindered of their little Manufactures which do not really injure any People in <hi>England;</hi> than to prefer a Petition, which if it occaſion ſuch a Law as I have already mentioned, will in all human probability be ſo grand a Diſcouragement to the Sheep maſters of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that the Merchants and Manufacturers of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170932:38"/>will not find the tenth part of the Wool to be imported from <hi>Ireland,</hi> which in two or three Years they might have otherwiſe expected.</p>
            <p>But to conclude the whole, I am partly aſſured that the main Body of the People of <hi>England</hi> are of Opinion, that all effectual means ought to be uſed, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts may never grow upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and become again vexatious and chargeable to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland:</hi> and I think, I have ſufficiently demonſtrated that there can be no greater Service done to the main Body of the vulgar <hi>Iriſh,</hi> than the paſſing of the forementioned Law.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>Scotch,</hi> perhaps many in <hi>England</hi> may think, that they prove as good Truſtees in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of that Country; and that if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt there, were ruined or broken, Epiſcopacy depoſed, and Presbytery eſtabliſh'd, 'twould do as well. But I am confident all true Friends to the preſent happy Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> both in Church and State, will be of Opinion, that it will be much more prudential, and infinitely more advantageous to <hi>England,</hi> that the Government and Eſtates of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be continued in the Hands of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and we ſhould be preſerved in a Condition of ſtanding by <hi>England</hi> upon any occaſion, both with Men and Money (of which this Law muſt render us wholly uncapable) than that we ſhould for the bare proſpect of ſome poor inconſiderable Profit to ſome particular Perſons be weakened, and left at the Mercy of thoſe that 'tis known to the World, would have but little Compaſſion upon us, could they be aſſured of carrying their point againſt us.</p>
            <p>This, I ſay, I believe will be the Opinion of the great, the wiſe, Counſellors, and Senators of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> to whoſe Wiſdom I moſt humbly ſubmit what
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170932:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>I have written upon this Subject, and refer the further confideration of what the Conſequences of ſuch a Law, as I have already ſo often mentioned, may be to that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and even to <hi>England</hi> it ſelf: and whoſe Conſultations, I pray God to direct to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his own Glory, the good of his Church, the honour of his Sacred Majeſty, and the ſafety and welfare of theſe Kingdoms.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAG. 25. lin. 21. read <hi>than thoſe.</hi> p. 33. l. 3. for <hi>that</hi> r. <hi>tho'.</hi> p. 37. l. 23. for <hi>Maſters</hi> r. <hi>Owners,</hi> p. 44. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. dele <hi>Families.</hi> l. 31. r. 30000. p. 69. l. 23. dele <hi>two.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
